Naked's what I call my way of cooking.
What I cook in the restaurant isn't
what I cook at home.
Cooking's gotta be a laugh.
It's gotta be simple
- it's gotta be tasty
- it's gotta be fun.
I suppose you could say it's stripping
down the recipe to its bare essentials.
No way it's not me it's the food.
You're up very early this morning Jamie.
Yeah it is a bit early isn't it -
no I've got my girlfriend Jules
coming round for lunch today -
I've been neglecting her
a bit lately so er -
down the flower market...
and get some nice flowers -
see if I can er -
make up some lost ground.
Are you gonna cook anything special?
Yeah yeah -
I've got a really nice fish dish -
a really good one and er -
I'm gonna do like baked chocolate tart -
which is like spot on so -
she's made for chocolate anyway so...
Supposed to be an aphrodisiac
isn't it chocolate?
Hi - could I have a couple of the white
and one of the light blue please.
Lovely - thank you very much -
cheers mate - bye.
Right this chocolate tart
is a real cracker.
I've gotta sweet pastry tart shell -
in the freezer, completely frozen -
just gonna whack it in the oven for
about 10 minutes so it's slightly golden.
Er - cos it's frozen
it doesn't seem to shrink -
that's a bit of a trick and er -
I'll get on with the filling.
So I need some butter -
unsalted butter - I need 140 grams.
And I'll just guess it -
it's about normally about 3/4 of a pack
and I just weigh it to check.
Ooh bad guess. I'm losing it.
Let's try again.
That's right - so 140 grams of butter and
then I've got the chocolate here yeah.
It's dark chocolate.
It's 70% cocoa solids which is -
basically this is the best stuff
I could get in the supermarket.
So it's 150 grams of chocolate in there.
I'm gonna need a pinch of salt in there.
Just a little one.
When I worked in France I worked with
this really good French patisseriere
and he always used to say to me - er
when you cook with chocolate
you must always put er
a little pinch of salt in there
and it brings out the flavour
in the chocolate
which is like a chocolate bases
and er one we sold without
and it made all the difference -
it really made it lovely jubbly and yummy.
So - pinch of salt.
Cocoa.
I need 8 sort of levelish
tablespoons of er
here we are
eight levelish tablespoons of cocoa powder
and that's gonna give it
a really good bitterness.
Er - but by the time we've put
all the other stuff in there
it won't be horribly bitter -
it'll just there in the background.
So do you think
chocolate tart is something
you'd always make it you wanted
to impress a girlfriend?
I think it's a good thing for the girls
cos the girls tend to be er -
rather into the old chocolate you know.
Yeah definitely.
I think it's quite a romantic
thing you know - chocolate.
I'm just gonna put a little
bit of water in a pot.
Er - put it on a little heat.
And let it melt slowly.
Just forget about it -
give a stir every couple of minutes.
Butter, the chocolate, the cocoa,
the salt all mixed up -
be nice and shiny and lovely.
That's basically the base
for the cake yeah -
where all the flavour's at -
that's where it's all happening.
What we need to do now
is get the other side of the cake
which is kind of the lift and the texture.
And for that I've got four eggs -
large, free range.
Nice yellow yolks you know.
Now I need to put
200 grams of sugar in that.
Castor sugar.
Just whisk it up.
One dissolve the sugar and also
to get a little bit of air in the there
and give the whole texture sort of
like a really kind of light pale,
fluffy consistency.
So are you planning quite
a romantic day today for Juliette?
Yeah well kind of -
it's a bit of a miserable day
so I'm a bit annoyed at that.
But er - yeah
I'm gonna make a nice lunch -
go out for a nice walk.
Chill out.
Might do something nice in the evening.
Just spend a bit of time together really.
Bit of quality time.
Try and get in the old good books
again mate - get out the dog house.
Right, so that's nice and smooth yeah.
And then we've got
two little secret ingredients
which are a bit different from the norm.
Got some sour cream and some golden syrup.
And basically - the old sour cream
gives a lovely kind of acidity -
little bit of a sourness which is
beautiful - makes all the difference.
Lightens it up a little bit and
I want three tablespoons of that.
You can use creme freche if you wanted.
The sour cream's slightly more yoghurty.
Creme freche is probably a bit more creamy
but they both have that really wonderful
sort of acidity which is lovely.
And then we've got this golden syrup -
nice traditional sort of ingredient.
Quite old fashioned really?
Quite old fashioned yeah -
but I tell you what this -
it gives this tart yeah?
It gives it a nice kind of toffeeness
which is good for flavour
but also you know gives it
that little bit of a chew.
And I like all that.
Makes a bit of a difference and
three tablespoonsish of that.
Must be fantasic having
a boyfriend who can cook?
You reckon?
You tell that to my girlfriend.
She just thinks I'm a bit strange.
The other day she came walked in
and found me watching -
the telly was on and
she found me watching the rotisserie
and the roast chicken just going around.
She thought I was really
weird and very sad.
So just mix this up together.
Just until it's smooth basically.
Right - so that's all done.
That's all mixed up.
Let's just check on the old choc.
...can use this spoon again.
Nearly there.
So this is where all the chocolate
is really like mega flavours.
Just lovely and shiny.
Right so now I will get my spatula
which is a bit of a handy tool in er -
in the dessert situation because it means
you can get everything out of the bowl
and why it's important to get everything
out of the bowl is cos like desserts
and baking and stuff is a bit more
like chemistry as opposed to cooking.
Now whereas you're doing sort of roast and
meals and stuff you can be a bit more -
you can personalise it
a bit more freely and do
what you like but quite important
to weigh everything you know
what I mean otherwise you find
that either doesn't taste as nice
or it hasn't risen or something like that.
Which is always a bit of a downer.
Ever had any terrible disasters?
Oh mate - I've had so many disasters
you wouldn't believe - I've lost count.
I've had so many bad ones.
Yeah - I mean
I make all my mistakes at home.
I try to anyway.
Right - that's looking good -
right - tart shell.
So the tart shell I put in
for about 10 minutes I suppose -
just until it's slightly golden
and we know it's just about cooked.
But we're gonna plunk
this straight in there now
and it's gonna go mad - absolutely mad.
The chocolate's gonna puff up -
look absolutely pukka.
Just carefully put it in the old oven -
I normally spill it at this stage.
And I cook it for about 40 minutes
at about 150 - be spot on.
I'm gonna make a really,
really fantastic salad -
it's so simple I'm almost
embarrassed to tell you about it.
But basically it's
a combination of raddish -
quite mustardy and fennel -
really nice and aniseedy -
really like crisp - little gem of a salad.
What's I'm gonna do right -
get myself a bowl.
I got these from the supermarket.
It's a really good thing cos like
just lately in the supermarket
I mean like over the last 2 years, er -
like we've got loads and
loads of radishes all a sudden.
Like we used to have
to have the boring old round ones.
Now we've got oval ones and we've got
oval ones with sort of white bits
and they look funky and
some are really mustardy
and some aren't quite so mustardy.
You get those big er - what they called -
mouly sort of like the Asian type ones -
black ones, white ones.
No it's just brilliant.
I think they're terribly,
terribly underrated and really,
really tasty.
So what I do is basically
these have got lovely leaves on - er -
I've given 'em a wahs.
There's no dirt of anything on -
I just cut the stalks off
about an inch above the raddish
and as far as
I'm concerned that is perfect.
I wanna eat all of that -
you know there's no point
in chopping in all away
and then what I do is
just slice off one end
and then I roll it onto that flat edge
and then just slice
as fine as I possibly can.
Is it something that goes
very well with fish - this?
Oh you wouldn't believe
how good it goes with fish.
If you imagine like the nice
sort of fragrant tasty old fish
and then this kind of zing
really nice sort of crunch salad.
I mean to me that
just makes complete sense.
And that's what cooking's
all about really you know -
you don't just do things because they're
fashionable or cos you're told to -
you do things cos you like to eat them
together do you know what I mean?
I've got some leaves here.
Right - and you just
pick out any dodgy ones -
I won't want all of them
but I'm gonna keep about half of them.
Just er - finely slice 'em.
They're really tasty as well.
And we always chuck 'em away in England.
I don't know why -
nothing wrong with it at all.
They're quite like sorrel -
almost you know quite a fresh flavour.
What does sorrel taste like?
You know when you put
a battery on your tongue -
gives you that kind of zing -
well it's kind of like
a very light version of that -
it's quite zingy -
quite juicy, quite fresh.
And er - basically quite nice.
And I'll show you these old fennels -
look at these.
Absolutely fantastic.
You can do anything with this.
You can roast it.
You can stew it - you can pan fry it.
You can do what you like with it.
It's really, really fantastic.
But in salads they're brilliant and
I'm just gonna take the old bottom off.
Right - and normally you can
pick that old bit off -
put it in stocks or whatever.
In actual fact I'll keep that - er -
and put that in the fish.
It'll add loads of flavour and then
round the top just take it off and er -
I've got these bits
left over in actual fact
I'll put those in the old fish as well.
That's - some people chuck that away
and it makes me really angry.
It's like the herby part and they're
absolutely fantastic - really delicate -
really good looking -
really fresh looking,
so we'll keep them for salad.
What I'll do is put
the old fennel on a flat edge
and just slice it
as thinly as you possibly can.
Just keep turning it onto its flat edge
and you just get really nice big shaves.
And if you've got one
of the mandolin things
you can use one of those - be bit careful.
The raddish and the fennel -
they're quite strong flavours
aren't they both them?
Yeah - well I mean
I think they're fantastic.
I mean the thing is right
sometimes flavours like have a bit
of a ruck do you know what I mean
and it doesn't work,
but quite frankly I reckon these are
like best mates do you know what I mean.
They have a real good laugh together
and I think it really works.
And you know sometimes it works
like that and sometimes it doesn't.
But whop all that in there.
The old fennel tops just
roughly or finely chopped.
Chuck 'em in there and
then I want some oil -
just about two or three tablespoons -
basically just enough
to cover what you've got.
Er - I probably need about a lemon -
one lemon for this - er -
but you do it to taste normally.
I don't want any pips they're horrible.
Get that in there and then at a guess
I wanna good pinch of salt.
A good pinch of pepper and
then just mix it all together.
And the colours you know I can feel
it's lovely and crunchy and actually -
just get a plate -
Get all this nicely mixed up
and let's have a little taste.
Ah yeah - that's -
I know this is the most simple
recipe in the whole wide world,
but to me things like that, that work
just sum cooking up all for me -
especially at home,
you want things to be simple,
you want really good results.
And I'm just well chuffed with that.
That's what cooking's all about.
And so quick?
So quick mate - I'm excited.
See you after long time -
it's nearly 3 weeks.
You look smashing.
Really nice you look.
So you ask me to make something
really nice for you?
Yes mate - I'd like some
of your lovely bread -
just a little loaf or something.
Oh my God!
You always do exactly the same thing every
- always go over the top.
You pick him up and you say Juliette...
Because I'm busy and you know
you're busy as well...
That's beautiful mate.
- Okay look after yourself - chow.
Take care.
Chow Bella!
I wanna do some new potatoes
to go with the fish.
I'm doing it really really simply
but there's a real kind of knack
of doing if really, really good.
And what I did - I got my new potatoes
and I give 'em a scrub
with a green scrubber -
so that kind of layer of skin has come
off and it kinda leaves it a bit rough.
So when you put all the lovely oil and
herbs and lemon juice on later it just...
it just coats it -
sucks it all up and just -
the all round potato tastes
absolutely beautiful
so what I've done is
I've just boiled them once -
after I've scrubbed them
in salted boiling water.
And I've got some really nice dill.
All I do is just pick off
all the nice bits,
get rid of the horrible fat stalks.
Tell you what is was so nice of Genoa?
To do that you know -
bake the bread for me.
He's done it for me -
he does it for me all the time.
But Italians are so romantic and you tell
him you're cooking for your girlfriend
and they start doing heart
shapes and big ones and -
kind of makes me feel a bit
bad about all the times
I've stitched him up at work.
I remember once we had a big shipment
of the white truffles come in
cos he was a mushroom man -
he used to deal with all that
and they're like 1400 a kilo
and he was kind of brushing them and
weighing them to make sure that ship -
you know the shipment was er -
you know all above board and so on -
the old invoice - and the phone
went and he went to answer it
and I went and swapped about a 1000 worth
of truffles for new potatoes and er -
when he came back he started realising
that things weren't quite right
and he started sniffing 'em and groping
'em and started swearing in Italian
and I disappeared the fridge
kind of like really laughing
looking through the kind
of joint in the door.
Then after about three minutes
of that he turned round
and saw me like really like
laughing my head off
in the corner in the fridge and er -
ran over and said
don't ever do that again -
you nearly give me a heart attack!
Oh God I feel bad.
Right so just chop this - er - dill up -
...kind of rough and then
just chuck it in an old bowl.
See how these are going.
Yeah - the nice thing about
really good new potatoes is that
they should be almost creamy -
do you know what I mean -
these are really... good - mmm -
Shake off all the steam.
But we'll let 'em go for a minute
but while they're still hot
we're gonna dress them
and that's just gonna make 'em taste
so good you wouldn't believe.
And the funny thing is it's really simple
things like a little bit of scrubbing,
dressing 'em while they're hot -
things like that,
that make things taste so much better
and people always go what did you do?
So you think it's the little things
in cooking that make the difference?
I think it's the little things and
the little bit of care that counts.
Just put 'em in - bit of dill -
squeeze over a lemon.
Olive oil -just a little lug -
enough to coat.
Salt and pepper.
And just dress it - or toss it -
mix it up - whatever you want to call it.
Would you use any other herbs
other than just dill?
Oh God yeah -
I mean like - things like dill
and mint are like the classic sort
of new potato partners you know -
but things like parsley when it's really
good and fresh er - basil's lovely.
You could do coriander
if you're in the mood.
Just anything -
any sort of delicate herb really.
This is an absolutely
fantastic way to cook fish.
The trick is that is we make
a tin foil envelope and we cook -
that means we cook everything in it -
got the herbs, got the fish -
got the lemon juice -
we've got the oil and
all these things cook away
and basically you've got
your main course meal
and you've got the sauce all made for you.
Roll out a bit of tin foil
four times bigger than your fish right.
Basically it's because
we're gonna double wrap
it just to be safe you know
so it's a nice thick bag.
Fold it in half like that
and then I've got a really nice fish.
It's a lovely sea bass.
And I went to the fishmonger
and I've had it scaled
and gutted for me so I haven't
got to do any of that malarkey.
It's about 2 pound which is more
than enough for me and Jules.
You normally - you lose about a pound
like at least half in bones and stuff.
Do you always make this dish with
whole fish or could you use steaks?
Oh you could use whatever you like -
you can use cuts -
I like to use whole fish
when I possibly can
because all the kind of bones within it
kind of help to make the meat really tasty
and the juice really tasty
and juicy as well you know.
So I'm must scoring it at
an angle - not deeply at all -
just a little bit thinly
and what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna get a good pinch of salt
and I'm gonna sprinkle that
on the fish on both sides -
I'm gonna kind of go against the grain
and push that into those gaps.
And do that on both sides.
And that's to get in all
that flavour right in there.
And then a good pinch of pepper
on both sides and do exactly the same -
just push that right in there
and you know that -
that's what it's all about really.
Little things like that make
things really, really tasty.
So what I need now is kind of the really
delicate kind of flavour enhancers
and you can do what you like
you know let your imagination take -
take you really,
but I've got some bay leaves.
I've got this red onion.
I've got these bits of fennel
that were left over from the salad
which were a bit stringy.
And some fresh basil which is good -
really, really nice basil.
Now what I'm gonna do
is finely chop this fennel.
And we probably won't eat this fennel -
you could but we probably won't eat it
because you know I just want it
to enhance the sauce really.
And then all you've gotta do is just
mix it all up a bit and then make -
lay it all out -
kind of equally over here.
Pat it all down.
And then put the fish on top of it -
like just like a trivet?
If you're roasting a bit of meat
or something like that.
And just push it to one end.
Why do you do that?
To keep the bottom of the -
the bottom side of the
bass off all the liquor
and the juice cos you don't want it -
you don't want the top sort of steaming
lovely and bottom kind of boiling away.
And I'm gonna peel -
peel an onion and slice it really thinly
and these red onions seem
to be nice and - and sweet.
And the thing about red onion as well -
when you cut it quite thinly
and it's a really delicate taste.
Just break it up a little bit
and just kind put it all around -
and I tell you what we will do -
we'll put a little bit
of salt in the cavity -
in the actual cavity of the fish -
just before we put anything inside it
and then we'll shove some onion in there.
And just push all these
things tight next to it
so they all kind of hug in it really.
And then what I want is
I've got lovely basil -
you know I wanna stuff that cavity
right full of lovely fresh herbs
and keep the stalks on -
you can bruise 'em
or snap 'em or break 'em just
to get the flavours going a bit.
But just stuff that right in there -
full you know like well OTT you know.
But just imagine all those
flavours in the belly -
all kind of steaming
as it cooks into the belly
and then you know all this
around it making that lovely juice
which is so tasty.
And then pick all these bits of bay leaf -
just kind of rip 'em over.
What other combinations of fish
and flavouring could you make?
There's so many - you can just let your -
just let your imagination go wild.
I mean - you can do like Monk fish
studded with anchovies - rosemary,
white wine, butter - you can do...?
...with cherry tomatoes and olives -
you can do Salmon with asparagus and mint.
You can do - you can do Cod with chick
peas and chillie and lime and parsley.
You can do - give me another thing?
Trout?
Give me trout - smashed up thyme
and lemon - very, very nice.
You know all wrapped up in a bag -
goodness - cook 'em away.
They're all fantastic
like that but you know
if you like two things together then think
well can I incorporate it into the bag.
I mean this can be a simple
or as complex as you want.
I mean if I just did this
with like flat leaf parsley
and lemon it would still
be gorgeous you know.
And no washing up either?
No just chuck it all away - no washing up.
And I like that cos I - you know
I'm not partial to scrubbing I must admit.
Nice lug of olive oil.
And what we want is
a good knob of butter -
about a good two,
three ounce knob of butter.
You can put it on it - inside of it -
er - you know around it - whatever.
And then the final thing that
makes it really really work -
is about two or three lemons -
two juicy ones of three
if they're not so juice.
And this lemon's gonna -
well it's gonna flavour it
but it's also gonna melt
with the old butter
to make the most outrageous
sauce you can imagine.
Get it all on there.
All done -just push the
old fish forward a little bit.
You can't really go wrong here
unless you're really rough and you -
and you pierce the tin foil.
So fold it over in half -
just like you would like an envelope or -
or a Christmas present
or something like that.
And push the two ends together
and then really tightly and firmly fold
cos you don't want this to leak.
Right - and then you go to one end -
just until you can start
to feel the flesh you know.
And then the last one
right
and then the last trick is just where
you've folded it just kind of bring it up
so it's not kind of
flopping onto the tray -
so there aren't any little gaps
then it won't escape.
Right and that's it -
all done - all raring to go.
Just gent... very, very carefully -
you don't want to pierce it now -
put it onto the old tray - in the oven -
220 degrees - 8 minutes per pound.
Two pound fish - 16 minutes -
so whack it in the oven -
when it comes out the oven
the little trick is actually that -
let it rest for about
three or four minutes.
Let it chill out.
And that just makes it taste a lot better.
Take it out to the table -
it's all puffed up.
Whip it open - steam ...