Naked's what I call my way of cooking.
What I cook in the restaurant isn't
what I cook at home.
Cooking's gotta be a laugh.
It's gotta be simple
- it's gotta be tasty
- it's gotta be fun.
I suppose you could say it's stripping
down the recipe to its bare essentials.
No way - it's not me it's the food.
You're early - what's this -
the element of surprise -
come in have a cup of tea.
What are you up to today Jamie?
Well I've got my uncle Alan coming round -
and he's bringing all my cousins with him,
and he's popping off to the boat show,
so I'm sort of left baby-sitting
so I've gotta keep them amused - er -
but they're gonna come back later and
I'm gonna cook them some dinner
so I wanna make a -
we're gonna have a bit of a pasta feast -
and I'm gonna make
two different types of ravioli
and a thing called semi freddo
which is pretty much like ice cream
but a bit more funky.
So I'm gonna go and see my mate Patricia
who's got a really nice cheese shop
cos the pasta's got
quite a bit of cheese in it
and she always really looks after me,
so I'd better get cracking really -
I've gotta get dressed -
I'm gonna knock up a bit of lunch before
I go out and er - get on with the day.
Right I'm gonna make this really
fantastic spaghetti dish -
it's like a real good munchie kind
of lunchie snackie kind of thing.
Let me show you how to do it.
I'm gonna make the pangrattato -
and we're gonna sprinkle it
on top of the pasta afterwards
and it's gonna give it a really,
really pucker texture.
What it is is crispy bread crumbs -
you can use fresh bread
if you want but I personally -
it's not as good really cos
you have to fight for longer then -
but er - dried stuff is idea.
So just cut most of the crust off -
don't be too worried about it.
You can rip it up - chop it up -
do what you like but I'm just gonna
whiz it - whiz it in here.
Just pulse this right -
And get some olive oil and get it
like a four or five second lug -
about four tablespoons.
Oil's getting hot -
couple of cloves of garlic -
So anyway - we need some thyme now.
You can get it everywhere.
Just pick it at the end here -
right and just whoop down like that -
and it's really tasty -
you know it's a really kind
of earthy kind of herb.
Doesn't matter what you do with thyme -
if you put it into oil
it always spits so be careful,
but it's not the end of the world.
Right - now these are in -
put your bread crumbs in -
stir them about a bit and this is -
this is really quick -
this takes about a minute
to get really crispy.
You can see all that's
getting nice and golden now.
I'd say this is just about perfect.
The littler bits are dead crispy and the
bigger bits are quite chewy and that's -
you know that's a nice thing.
That gives character.
So that's - that's hot.
Leave that to cool down.
Right - so what I need to do now -
I'm gonna cook the pasta
and make the sauce.
Water's boiling.
Right for this sauce
I'm gonna show you how simple it is.
All it is is anchovies - I've got -
I've got some dried chillies here -
a lemon and what else do we need?
- I need garlic.
Couple of tablespoons of olive oil.
Put your garlic in.
And just fire off the garlic -
not until brown or anything -
but just so it softens up.
These particular chillies are just
fresh ones that I've dried at home
and they're not that -
they're not really that strong.
About five anchovies.
Jiggle it around a bit.
Then all you do is just get a nice lemon -
I've taken most of the pips out.
Funnily enough it's the lemon that
makes it work cos I never kind anchovies
but you don't - when they melt away
they don't really taste like that.
You get the lovely heat from the chillie -
right just check this pasta again -
yeah looks pretty well.
Mmm - perfect.
Right - I'm gonna drain this -
and then when it's still steaming hot
put it into that sauce.
And you just swill it about
and take it off the heat now -
I'll turn the gas off.
And like that's all coated
in like all the sauce -
it's shiny and it's just really tasty.
So just whack it in a bowl.
No mucking about -
scrap out all the juice.
Get all these crispy bits and
just er - look at that - oooh...
You know that tastes nice don't you?
What are you laughing at?
That's how you're supposed to eat it.
Actually I like these so much
I'm gonna have some more.
And in cooking it won't be lost.
Very soft isn't it?
Unfortunately - very very fresh.
I like fat men.
You like men with a bit of meat on?
Absolutely.
Well give me six more months -
I might be there.
This is strong white flour.
And so I do 500 grams.
Like everything there's different
recipes but this is one that is very,
very reliable and damn good.
So what I'm gonna do - 500 grams -
you can make -
you can make this by hand in a bowl.
It's just as easy.
I'm gonna do it in this cos it
just takes a little bit of work away.
I put two whole eggs in and
then I'm gonna put 8 egg yolks
and the reason that I'm putting
8 yolks in as opposed to 4 eggs is
because the extra yolk
I feel give it a certain richness
which is just really beautiful.
It's really silky, gives a wicked colour
and I just think you know it makes it
what fresh pasta is really -
that richness.
Right -
so basically just gonna turn it out.
Doesn't look much like pasta now.
Looks like broken up... biscuits?
Yeah but then you squeeze it
and then you start to work it.
And now you just put all your weight
into it and just keep doing this
and it'll come together
as a quite dry dough.
Keep giving it some
until it goes smooth and silky.
So that's done really.
So just warp it up -
push it out and put it in the fridge
for about half an hour.
Let it rest and then we can carry on.
Right so the pasta's had about
half an hour to rest.
Er - it's softened up a little bit,
it's - it's a little bit -
you know it's gonna be a lot
more pliable now cos it's relaxed.
Make sure you've got a nice clean surface.
I mean you only need about that much space
but I'm lucky I've got a bit longer
and you need one of these machines
and they're about 20 quid
and you can get them
absolutely everywhere.
It's like a mangle.
But they've got little notches here yeah -
that go up and down and
that gets thinner and fatter.
So look - look at that lovely dough.
Right we're gonna divide this by four
and basically put three back
because we don't want these to get dry
and it's nice and soft
and if the air gets to that
it'll from a skin
and that'll be horrible to roll out then.
So just roll -
wrap those up and with this one -
you just wanna with your hand
or rolling pin
if you want just kind of
level it out a little bit.
And then it's gonna be really easy
to sort of put through the machine
without too much grief.
Put it on its thickest setting
and we just run it through
quite slowly on the first time.
See
- So now we'll start
working down one by one.
Some people find it easier if you dust it.
I'm not a great lover
of dusting it too much
but if you just do
a little bit and then right...
What does that do for it then?
Well it - some people put loads on
but I just put it on
and wipe off the excess and
it just stops it from sticking to this
and then when it comes out of this end
and it gathers up stops it
from sticking at that end as well.
Right so if I leave it now -
it's getting a bit thinner and
it's kind of building up here.
So you wanna kind of pull it
in a bit there and flatten it out -
give it a little bit of tension.
And you can get a little bit there -
see it's pulling in a bit there -
so just pull it in this bit.
And there you go - lovely.
This is done basically now.
Normally I just -
I'd make the ravioli straight away now
but you know if time's not on your side
then make it now in the morning,
and er - you know I can do my fillings
a little bit later and if you er -
layer this up quite tightly
like this on a plate -
a little bit of flour - and er -
cling film it tightly
so the air doesn't get to it -
it'll probably keep in the fridge
for a couple of hours - really well.
I always make this amount -
even if I'm just making it for myself
because even if you're only using
a little bit you can make some more pasta
and I've got it like dried up
there you know -
just taglitelli -
papadelli whatever you want.
I'm gonna make the dessert now.
It's a thing called semi freddo
which at home is definitely
the nearest best thing to ice cream.
It's very flexible you can do
any flavour you like.
And I'm gonna do praline
which is basically caramel
and roasted hazelnuts
which to me is just like the best combo.
So what I need is 200 grams
of castor sugar -
it's not a hot pan but it's heating up now
and I need about
3 or 4 tablespoons of water.
And what this is gonna do
is loosen up the sugar,
make it a syrup
and let me show you the hazelnuts.
I've just roasted them
until lightly golden.
If you look at this sugar it's starting
to colour round the outside very slowly.
And then you just splish it about a bit,
so it's even.
Don't be too aggressive -just gently.
So what's Uncle Alan like
who's coming round today?
Uncle Alan?
Everyone says that
he used to look like Cliff Richard.
Cliff Richard! - But er -
I don't think he looks that
much like Cliff Richard but -
well he certainly can't sing anyway.
No there's no way
Alan could be like Cliff Richard
cos Cliff Richard never got married
and Uncle Alan's had three wives.
This caramel now is light golden -
carefully pour them in.
And what we're gonna do now
is just cook it for about another minute.
Slush it about a bit.
Cook it for another minute and
then look at how gorgeous that looks -
it's shiny and golden
and what we're gonna -
we're just toasting the nuts now
and they're both kind of impregnating
the flavour into each other really -
the caramel's getting hazelnut and
the hazelnut's getting caramel.
So I'm gonna put it on a metal tray
but I mean er you can put it
on a plate or anything
that's not gonna melt really.
And just put a bit of sunflower oil on -
just a little drib -
rub it in and
this'll stop it from sticking.
And that's ready.
Superb - so just pour it in the middle -
try and get all the sugar out -
be careful not to drip any on yourself
cos that would be very hot.
And then just with the bottom
of your spoon just push it out.
So they're all flat and then
they'll cool down nice and quick.
Right so this praline's been
cooling down now for about 25 minutes
and as you can see
it's like a big biscuit -
it's like - it's all completely solid.
But the really - listen listen -
and that's the nice thing
about the metal actually
it's a little bit flexible
which means you can kind of...
just whack it in here
and then like pulse it.
Perfect.
You've got powder and you got bits
of chunk in there which is ideal -
loads of flavour - loads of texture.
So I can forget about this now -
that's the nice things -
flavour done - right -
and let me just make the semi freddo.
We need four eggs yolks -
I need 50 grams of sugar -
okay - shove it in there.
Straight in there and just whish
these together until they both pale.
Right now it's a bit paler -
I'm gonna add some vanilla and
a good one should be sort of soft -
not dry - soft and slightly sticky
if you're really lucky
and you just cut it near enough the tip -
all the way down the middle right -
and then inside
you've got all the beans here -
you just get the point of your knife
and just run it right to the end
and you get all of that
and it's dead pucker.
Just scrap it on the old whish.
To me vanilla pods is probably
one of the most amazing ingredients -
in the kitchen I just think it's stunning.
You wouldn't use vanilla essence
would you for this?
No, - it just smell so different.
Anyway don't chuck away
these cos obviously 70p each
they're worth quite a bit -
pop it in a little pot of sugar and
that'll infuse its flavour into the sugar
then you've got vanilla flavoured sugar.
Just look at that.
All those black dots -
I mean how funky is that?
It is isn't it?
But again just whisk like mad
and it'll get slightly thicker
and a little bit more paler.
Beautiful right - double cream -
500 millilitres.
When this cream gets like nice and thick -
sort of ribbon stage - like that see?
- Not thin anymore is it?
We're ready to rock and
roll with the egg whites.
Okay - the thing is with the egg whites -
just a little pinch of salt -
just before you start whipping and
You can't taste that though can you?
No you can't taste it
but what it does is it -
it does something to the eggs and
it makes it capture the air more
and be stiffer which is exactly
what we want so -
So look you can see it getting
bigger and bigger already.
Not quite.
Nearly.
See - wicked.
Right we've got loads of air in the egg -
got loads of air in the cream and
we've made a lovely flavour right -
so what we do is we just pour
most of this praline - most of -
leave a bit into the cream and just pour
all these egg whites on top of that -
and very gently fold it in -
you're not being aggressive with it -
do you know what I mean
you're just folding in the flavours
just to kind of gently mix it together.
If you bang it together with a whish
or even with a spoon all that air
that you've just been trying
to put into the egg whites
and the cream just disappears
and you can hear it bubble
and you don't want that so just fold it
in and when you're just about there -
and have a little scoop round
the middle to make sure you haven't -
there see that there -
got a bit there -just scoop it in.
Now I'm quite happy with that now -
there's some chunks of stuff
there but I like -
I like it quite marbled.
You could use that praline
for all sorts of other things.
I'm sure couldn't you?
Oh God - you use pralines for everything -
and all you have to do is get
some really nice vanilla ice cream -
nice big ball of that
and sprinkle it on top
and it tastes wicked I tell you what
I have done sometimes actually - er -
got a couple of packets of Maltesers
and this sounds really,
really drab but you just whiz 'em up
so they're like chunky powder
and put them on top -
and they're really nice -
I tell you really, really tasty.
Scrap it all from the sides -
yeah -just shake it
so it levels out a little bit
then with this left over praline
just sprinkle it on top.
I know the kids are gonna love that -
right up their alley.
Just chuck it in the freezer -
bout - I suppose it will be ready
in about 40 minutes.
Hello mate you alright?
Nice to see you -
looks like you've got
the short straw today eh?
Have a nice time at the boat show and
you gonna come by for some food later?
Take care - see you mate.
How's it going girls alright?
Right I am making the fillings for
the ravioh and I'm making two fillings.
First one is potato, water cress
and cheeses from Patricia
which will be lovely jubbly
and the potatoes are ready
so I'm just gonna drain these and
I've also put in four cloves of garlic
which I've taken the outside off.
I'll show you one.
And when they're cooked with the potatoes
- see how soft they are see - wicked. So.
Do you leave those in then?
Yeah leave them in cos they've got
no skins or anything like that
but when garlic cooks like that
it gets very, very mild and er -
I think it just adds a good edge
to the potatoes really -
so let them drain for about
three or four minutes -
let all the moisture sort
of evaporate off and -
so I've got some really nice gorgonzola
and some pecarino from Patricia.
Lovely - that's gorgonzola - it's really,
really nice - nice and crumbly.
Really tasty - quite a strong flavour
but when it's in with those potatoes
it's going to chill out a bit -
be really nice.
And I've got this pecarino which is
I suppose you could say you shouldn't say
but you could say
it's quite similar to parmesan.
It's slightly softer, nice and sweet -
not sweet sweet but sweeter.
Just chuck in there -
the garlic will go to you know to a paste
and mix in really well.
While this is hot I'm gonna get
all these flavours in there
so they're all kind of melting
and all the flavours are happening.
So I'm gonna use about
half of this to start with -
just gonna break it in there.
And this pecarino just take skin off -
That pecarino does look
a bit like parmesan.
Yeah but it's - it's softer -
it's hasn't been aged as long -
I really like it actually.
What I need to get now is some butter.
I'm just gonna use about an ounce
just to enrich it a little bit.
I've got some really nice watercress - er
What makes it really nice then?
Well just look at it - it's really green -
big fat leaves and it's really
mustardy and I love all that -
it's really pucker I've dumped it
in water like I do with basil -
shaken it about a bit
so it's nice and clean.
So let's put that in there -
this is gonna start
tasting really good now.
At this stage I mean it looks like
mashed potato doesn't it?
You imagine that with maybe
some more butter in it you know - er
with a nice bit of roasted cod
or like you know fish and... lovely.
I'm really happy with that -
so that's one filling done
I've got to check on the next filling -
so I'll go and see what the girls
are doing with the broad beans.
Superb.
Alright -
so I've got my lovely broad beans.
First things first - get the broad beans -
gonna go straight into boiling water.
And then absolutely no salt in there
because salt actually makes the outsides
of the broad bean get tougher
so we can just season it later - not now.
Now whereas the base for
the other ravioli was potato
and that was lovely jubbly
and it's finished,
this one is gonna be ricotta -
it's a very,
very crumbly kind of light cheese
and you know it's very very young.
It's not got loads and loads of flavour
but it's kind of fresh -
it's got like a real milky taste
and I like that.
So make sure it's really,
really fresh cos it does go off quite
quickly compared to other cheeses.
So I'm just gonna
put this ricotta in a bowl -
these have been in for about a minute
so
- gonna pour those in there.
Drain it off a bit.
I'm gonna try and finely chop some
and then leave the other quite coarse
and what happens then is that
you're kind of getting lots of texture
and you can see
what you're eating which is nice.
Also you're getting loads of flavour
in there as well and you want that.
What I'm gonna do is pour
this into the bowl -
you can put as much mint in as you like
but I just do it to freshen it up -
so you just keep tasting.
And it's funny cos this herb actually
makes the dish a lot lighter really tasty
and it goes with broad beans so well
so I'm just gonna chuck this in
with the broad beans -
it's still a little bit hot -
I can put a pinch of salt in now -
and a little bit of pepper cos
we didn't season that in water.
And give it a good little lug of olive oil
cos that'll get all the flavours happening
And just toss it over a bit.
Bout half a lemon.
What we've gotta do now
is grate some parmesan.
You only want a little bit -
about a handful.
Right so nice handful of that.
Get a fork and just fork it through
and you can see how crumbly
and light this ricotta is -
it's a wicked base for this.
And this is what I do -
is this mixture
just pour it all into here.
And just fold it in.
Fold it in and mash it up -
do whatever you have to do
to get it stuck in there
and you can see
it's got a brilliant colour now.
Just taste a bit.
Mmm - that's perfect so basically
we've got two fillings done -
and what I've gotta do now
is show you how to make a ravioli.
Just brush off the excess flour right -
and you get a little bit of your filling
and you want about a dessertspoonful
and then get a little bit of water -
brush round the edges -
all four sides and once you've done that -
look at the corners -
cos it's the water that's
gonna stick it all together
and that's really important
so don't forget it -
just fold it over, push it together
there so this side's now sealed.
Come over here and push that side together
cos that sides now sealed.
And then put your two little fingers -
curl your thumb round
and just do that and just -
and then you've just got one bit left.
Don't just b... it
cos you'll get a bit of air
stuck in there - you don't want that.
Start from one end,
and get rid of the air.
And there you have it -
perfect ravioli - no cracks,
no nothing and
then just take with a cutter,
just trim it off and what that does -
it doesn't just cut a pretty shape in it
it kinds of pushes the pasta together.
So it means it's not gonna burst open.
Could you use a knife?
Yeah you could use a knife -
in actual fact it's -
it's quite cool to use a knife as well
cos this is quite an obvious thing to do,
so I just chuck this straight
into boiling salted water -
give it about two minutes for that sort
of size and then just fish 'em out -
shake 'em off on a plate.
Come on girls give us a hand then.
Grab a plate and grab a spoon.
You watching.
This is like Blue Peter this is.
Grab a bit of filling about that much and
then put it in the middle of one side.
Not too much water though -
just brush round the outside of it.
What happened to your one?
Fold it over like that.
And then - then squeeze all around it.
So yours are wicked.
I think I'm gonna employ you -
bit of cheap labour.
Had a good time.
You haven't destroyed the place then?