Naked's what I call my way of cooking.
What I cook in the restaurant isn't
what I cook at home.
Cooking's gotta be a laugh.
It's gotta be simple
- it's gotta be tasty
- it's gotta be fun.
I suppose you could say it's stripping
down the recipe to its bare essentials.
No way - it's not me it's the food.
Right I've gotta have something to eat
before I do anything else.
I'm gonna have a bacon sarnie for breakie
so what I've don't is I've got one of
the grill pans and they're quite cheap -
I use it all the time now just for like -
meat, fish - so easy.
Anyway look I've got this bread here -
and er -
I get 'em to slice it on the machine
but you know you get in there
and get a normal bread loaf and you
get it cut across into the normal round,
well I do it the other way and I say
can you put it through the long way.
So what you get is this... look at that...
Have you got a big day today then?
I've got a huge day.
I used to be in this band
when I was from 14 to 17 -
then I moved to London to sort of work
in the kitchens and stuff and er -
we never really spoke -
well we spoke on the phone every now
and again - that was it.
But about six months ago
they all moved to London -
so we kind of got it back together again.
We've got the first gig tonight mate.
What instrument do you play?
I'm a cliche drummer -
little bit hyperactive -
talks rubbish most of the time -
big fidgety - what can I say?
Right I'm just gonna push
this bacon to one side now
cos that's cooked and it looks lovely.
And I'm gonna get this bread
and I'm gonna toast it - on here -
instead of toasting it normally
I'm gonna toast it on this grill pan
and that's gonna suck up
a little bit of all -
the fat and the juices that
comes up from the bacon.
Do you always use white bread?
No - I don't - well - yeah.
I don't like brown bread.
My mum always tried to get me on it
but I don't like it at all.
Are the band coming back
to eat this evening?
Yeah I'm gonna cook er -
a Thai green curry
which is pretty appropriate really
curries are kind of like the English boys
or Essex boys sort of ultimate after -
after pub food.
Right this is about done now.
Right I'm just gonna eat this
and then I've gotta go shopping
and get stuck in cos I've got a lot to do.
So what I'm gonna make is
a Thai green curry yeah -
and for that we have
to make a green paste.
It's very quick to make
and very quick to cook.
Well there's a little bit of
preparation at this point er -
so what we're gonna do is
we've got spring onions here -
I use about five or six.
Could you use normal onion?
Yeah use normal onions -
shallots
and then lemon grass
basically what we want is the inside
where it's slightly white -
slightly softer - loads of flavour
- really zesty.
So I'm just gonna trim off the bottom
and then just trim off the end
until the tender quite of the root
which about normally about half way down
and you just want to strip the outside
leave off - cos they're quite tough.
It's a really delicate flavour - er -
and even if you just put in
with steamed rice
and stuff like that the flavour of it
really kicks all the way through.
It's lovely.
Split in half and
just cut into about four bits.
All these together make
a really good taste yeah
but if there's an ingredient
that you particularly like -
like I'm getting quite partial to
the old lime leaves -just up 'em a bit.
But this is -
this is a good one that I like.
Then I need some garlic.
Two or three -just peel 'em -
we can leave them whole.
Ooops - oh no -
Then I've got the ginger yeah -
thing to look out for when
you get the ginger is you want
a nice big fat old hand of ginger -
cos sometimes you have to root
around these poxy little bits
and they're just stringy
and dried up and horrible.
Nice thick bit - and just rip it off -
you can peel it with
a peeler or use a knife.
Right - so we wanna about that much
you know about a tablespoon's worth.
And that's another thing done.
Right we've got limes yeah -
lovely, lovely limes.
Just peel off a little bit of the skin
cos the skin's quite
fragrant and there's no -
you know no point in chucking it away.
I've got these really pucker chillies.
I'm gonna use about four or five -
again up it or lower
it as to what you like.
I'm just gonna take the ends off -
and I'm gonna cut them in half.
Do you think there's quite a macho element
into how hot you like your food?
Yeah - well -er - I suppose
when you go out with the boys
and you get a bit bevved - it does -
well - it's been know to turn into
a bit of a competition like
who can have the hottest curry,
but I just love chillies though so much.
The really really hot curries they use
the whole chillie which are these seeds,
but it's hot but it doesn't
really taste of chillie.
If you take the seeds out -
you get a nice warmth there -
but the actual taste
of chillie comes through.
Right so next we're gonna use lime leaves
and they're kind of unusual -
you get 'em in every single Thai
or Chinese supermarket
and you're starting to get 'em
in the supermarkets now
but these make such a difference -
they've got a really authentic flavour,
and I just wanna a little
handful like that much
and you buy them in bags like this
and you can freeze 'em
and they keep so well in the freezer.
Take any big bits of stalk that are off
and you just roll 'em up
like a little cigar and er -
just chuck 'em across -
just to help the machine a bit...
Right so I've this coriander here
and you know you want about sort of
three really good handfuls of this -
so that bunch is perfect and basil -
just rip the stalks off -
leave some of them on.
And we wanna about you know
two really good handfuls of basil -
so we've got lots of
fragrance there you know.
Coriander seeds -
about a little handful
or you know tablespoon
and a half and
just crack them in half -
you don't want to smash
'em up to a powder.
Lovely. Right this is the easy bit.
Just take it over to the mixer
get me olive oil.
Put my ginger and
the kind of the rougher things -
the sort of tougher things.
So I've got the garlic in there,
the garlic, the spring onions.
The things that are gonna give
the machine a little bit more work -
just pulse it up basically
as fine as you can.
Add a good good pinch of salt
and a bit of pepper -
coriander in - coriander seeds.
Right so just cut these limes in half
and just squeeze all the juice in there -
all these herbs -
...just push it all down.
Put about two tablespoons -
three tablespoons worth of oil in.
Just leave it go for a couple of minutes.
Basically that's done now.
It smells absolutely outrageous.
Will you use all that paste for the curry?
I probably will use all this paste
cos I want you know
I'm gonna put coconut milk in -
I want lots of sort of juice -
but I tell you what -
even if I'm cooking for myself -
I still cook this much
because all you have to do is jar
it in an airtight container -
bit of oil over the top
so the air doesn't get to it
and it keeps for weeks in the fridge.
Right - I've got this really
nice chicken breasts yeah -
they're free range of course -
but you know get what you can.
Would you use the green paste
with any different sort of curry -
you don't have to use chicken?
The green paste? -
Oh God the green paste -
you can do so much with this -
I mean you can basically -
you can marinate like kebabs or something
and just have the paste on its own
and like barbecue it in the summer -
just put some lime juice
over it afterwards.
Use it with prawns to do
sort of prawn curries - er -
sort of you know
just brush bits of fish with it
and just sort of grill it really quickly.
So I'm just gonna cut them
at a sort of angle -
quite big bits and that'll make
a sort of a big bit of surface area
so it can have a nice
marinade clinging to it.
I'm gonna take about
I suppose a spoonful -
a couple of tablespoons of the m...
of the paste -
and -just put that in there.
I'm gonna put the chicken in with it
and I'm just gonna toss it over
and I only want it to lightly coat it.
So you don't put the chicken
in all the marinade?
No cos I just -
I want the flavour to impregnate the meat
I also want to just give it that -
initially when I cook it
I wanna give it that sear in a wok -
and if I've got too much of this
in it it's gonna boil.
Lovely - so this -
I'm gonna give this about
20 minutes of marinade -
that's the minimum
you wanna give it really.
But anything from 20 minutes
to 2 hours is great.
Right so I'm gonna cook the curry now -
it's very very simple.
I've got a hot wok -
get your meat ready -
get your paste ready.
Coconut milk - nearly forgot.
Put my oil straight in -
put it round the sides.
What sort of oil is that?
Just normal sort of vegetable oil.
In with the meat -
And just like - push it about -
we're just gonna cook it
like this for about 2/3 minutes -
just so we searing a little bit of colour
in and that - that's nice for flavour.
If you didn't have a wok could you do it
a saucepan or something?
Yeah of course you can -
do it in like a casserole type pan -
get it really hot again.
Exactly the same and then -
I'm gonna get this paste -
get it all in there and this is
where really you stop frying -
and start sort of boiling it now.
So just smear over that green paste.
Just for like 30 seconds or something
and then we'll add this coconut milk.
Brilliant.
And just stir it all in...
right - so basically
I'm gonna bring it to the boil -
right - let it simmer
for about 12/13 minutes -
just until the chicken's nice and tender -
and er - that's it - it's done.
Just season it to taste - a bit of lime -
get some sort of shaved coconut in there -
chopped pistachios nuts and some coriander
just to freshen it up at the last minute
and I think the band will really -
I think they're gonna love it.
I'm gonna make this really excellent
salad that goes with the green curry -
the green curry being quite fragrant
and hot and this salad being quite clean.
So what I've got here is
just some really nice
deep red perfectly ripe cherry tomatoes
and I'm just cutting them in quarters -
you can do 'em in halves if you want.
I've got a fresh coconut -
we don't want any of that
desiccated stuff.
Er - and as you can buy
these absolutely anywhere -
markets - supermarkets - whatever -
it's much better and much
more authentic to use these.
If you wanna keep the milk you can -
We put -
we only actually need half a coconut.
I can save this and scrap it
onto the curry later or just keep it.
Do something else with it.
So just cut if up into bits -
and slice it as thinly as possible
in any old fashion really.
You can see it's such a wicked colour.
Really tasty and...
tastes so much different
to the dried stuff -
don't even think about it.
Different textures as well -
it's not just taste.
Lovely - right so just chuck this in.
Next thing you need is we've got cucumber
and I need about - about half a cucumber.
Just peel this and then
I'm gonna cut it in half
and we want to remove this little bit
in here which is really watery -
tastes of kind of nothing really.
Really don't want it -
and you get a spoon -
scoop it out or you can get a knife -
just go in at an angle very gently -
go in at an angle here.
Just kind of turf it out and
just kind of use your fingers
till you can see all that -
just water - you don't want that.
I quite like to sort of cut it
in half again -
just do it in thin like kind
of length ways bits like that
and then just cut it in half again -
I just kind of think that size is perfect.
You know you want it the same as the...?
What else might you serve this salad with?
Well it's a very refreshing salad
so you always do it with light things -
things like er -
simply grilled piece of fish -
you know white fish preferably.
Simply grilled chicken - er -
cheeses you know - feta cheese,
ricotta, mozzarella - really nice.
Yeah just -just simple things really.
Er - So what we're gonna do now -
I've got some nice basil -
really fragrant that I bought
and I've washed it -
I just wanna about that much and that's -
it's quite strong and it's really fresh
and we're gonna get loads and loads
of flavour our of that so just -
just slice it up -
get that stuck in there.
Like you can smell it already
do you know what I mean? -
It's lovely jubbly.
Could you use any other herbs?
Yep - you could use coriander
which is lovely - coriander and basil -
but I've got a lot of coriander
in the green curry
and I wanna keep the flavours separate
so I think that makes sense
do you know what I mean.
Right so what I wanna do now is dress -
dress it like a normal salad -
a good pinch of pepper -
a good pinch of salt -
and I'm gonna use limes -
two limes and that's gonna give it a -
as opposed to lemon
it's gonna be really zingy.
Something that will help get the juice
out is just to put your weight on it
and roll it like that - roll it off and...
you've got that fragrance of the skin
straight away and you can peel the skin -
finely chop it and just put it
in a pan with some fish -
panned fried fish or something like that -
that'll work brilliantly.
But I don't want the skin.
I just want the juice and
just shove your hand inside
and give it a good old squeeze.
And then you wanna put about the same
amount of olive oil as the lime juice -
er - and now just give it
a little toss over.
Or you can mix it -
or get your hand stuck in -
just toss it over and
the colours are amazing
and what we're gonna do now
is just put your finger at the bottom
where all the kind of dressing
dripping down to -
and taste it - little bit more salt -
just so everything's like perfectly...
bit of pepper and -
I think - an optional now -
which I think I'll go for is er -
a little bit of chillie -
just split them in half and
scrap the seeds out the middle.
It gives it a little bit of heat -
not hot -
I'm not talking anywhere
near blowing your head off -
but what I'm talking about is
a really really nice sort of warmth
that works with the cucumbers and
the tomatoes and the limes and it just -
I think it brings it
all together really well.
Yeah - this will sit quite happily
for a bit of time -
letting all the sort of flavours
come out of the chillies
and everything to combine a bit
and it's you know
it's a really colourful thing -
in the middle of the table - lovely.
Right to go with my pucker curry right
I'm gonna make the perfect rice
and I know everyone knows
how to make rice -
but this is a special way that
I use to make it really light
and really fluffy and I like it.
Boil up the rice -
in boiling salted water
for about 4 or 5 minutes
and then at that stage the rice
is just slightly under cooked
and I put a little bit of
water back in the pan -
put the colander over it -
and whack it back on there.
Bit of tin foil over and basically -
water's draining off now and
it's gonna come to the boil
and start steaming again and that's gonna
really help to make it lovely and light -
takes about five minutes and then
it'll be perfectly ready to eat.
What I'm gonna make now
is a thing called tempura
which is basically is a really
really pucker crispy batter
and you can deep fry like
vegetables or meat or fish
but I'm gonna do vegetables
today with dipping sauces
and I think it's
the dipping sauce that really -
you got that big crunch and
you've got the lovely inside
but the dipping sauce is what you want
and I'll show you how to make -
it's very, very simple and
you can vary it any old way.
I've got rice wine vinegar here.
Rice wine vinegar's slightly more
mild than like white wine vinegar
but I mean you can use it.
What you've got to do is sweeten it
and it's very simple and
you can just do it to your own taste.
So if you just get a little bowl.
I'm gonna put in about half a pint okay -
and I'm gonna add about three kind
of dessertspoons of sugar to this
and you just stir it until it goes clear.
Just keep tasting - and -
what you wanna do is take that
harshness out of the vinegar -
so it's just beautiful for dipping.
Put a little bit more in I think - yeah.
Right so you've got your sweet
and sour there - that's there.
What we need to do now is get
loads and loads of flavour.
I've got coriander here -
just a little handful -
and this is how easy it is you know.
I'm just gonna chop it up
and whop it in there.
And I want some chillies -
just scrap out most of the seeds.
How did - how did the gig go?
The gig was superb mate honestly -
it was such a cracker
and it was a real laugh.
Got a bit sweaty though -
I like to get into it a bit.
Right kind of finelyish chopped -
in it goes.
Now garlic's quite important actually -
not much but just a little bit of garlic -
not garlic that's gonna
punch you round the face
but garlic that just kind
of changes the flavour -
it gives you that kind of -
I'm talking like a wine merchant -
And I probably use a quarter -
so just finely chop it -
and that'll be enough to make it
completely taste different.
Give it a good old stir round -
Right - yeah wicked.
Those flavours are really strong.
But of salt and pepper -
always important and
that tastes alright now -
but give it like ten minutes
or give it an hour -
that'll be like a tea-bag -
there'll be loads of flavours
all over the place.
So that's the dipping sauce done?
Yeah - end of story.
Just going to put it into
some little bowls - and er -
I'll put them in the middle of the table
and they can just dip away.
Now I'm gonna make the batter -
very important you've gotta
make it last minute.
All you need is cornflour
and plain or strong flour.
And what I need to do is I need
double normal flour to cornflour -
so it's one cup of cornflour
to two lots of normal flour.
Lovely - right okay.
We need water,
okay but we need ice cold water and if -
if you've got it hanging about -
fizzy mineral water or soda water
seems to give it a little bit of an edge.
But if not you know cold - very cold -
ice cold water is perfect.
It has to be ice cold?
It just helps it - it's like -
imagine we're gonna deep fry it yeah -
very hot -
imagine something
really cold hitting that -
it's just gonna go - straight away
it's gonna make it really crunchy so...
Some water - swish it around a bit -
let it cold cold.
Now -
this is the important bit about tempura.
We're not gonna let it -
we're not gonna make it and
let it rest like normal batters right.
We wanna make it right
at the last minute -
we're not gonna whip it
with a whish so it's really smooth -
I'm gonna use like the back
of a spoon of a chopstick
and what that'll give you
is kind of a lump batter
and I know that sounds really freaky
but the little lumps help
to make it really crispy
and it's quite characteristic
of tempura in general really.
Right so this -
this water's really cold now -
so what I'm gonna do is just pour it in -
add it bit by bit - stir it in slowly -
You want it to be about double cream -
just slightly thicker than
double cream consistency -
Lovely - that's perfect -
absolutely stunning.
Right so I've gotta wicked
selection of vegetable here.
I've got green beans, I've got chillies -
I've got mushrooms - I've got courgettes -
I've not asparagus -
we've got sweet potato - I've got onions.
I've got broccoli -
you know herbs - little corns -
so just get a bit of everything in there -
you don't want to overload the frying oil
so just kind of do little bits
at a time and use your -
your chop stick to kind of just
fold it all over -just to coat it.
And shake off any excess if there is any -
and this oil -
I've got hot oil here and
it's been heating up slowly -
this is at 200 - 220 degrees
It you haven't got a thermometer -
you can get 'em for about five quid -
all you have to do is dip it in
and if it kind of starts
to fry quite fast that's fine -
if it's a really viscous
fry you don't want that
and if it's not frying at all -
then it's too cold.
So just keep your eyes peeled.
Kind of flick it away from you -
just so that if any like splashes of oil
come in they don't go anywhere near your.
What sort of oil is it?
It's just normal like sunflower oil.
So you get your first load in quick -
otherwise they'll all be cooked
at different times.
What's your favourite vegetable in it?
I reckon my favourite
must be the chillies -
the mushrooms and the sweet potatoes -
I just love those - so good. So so tasty.
Right so I'm just gonna use one of
these things just to turn it over a bit
and don't be viscous with it
but just kind of like turn 'em over -
make sure they're not sticking -
move 'em about a little bit
and I just feel already
they're really really crispy.
The only thing that determines
how you should cut things up
is like for instance -
that batter cooks in about two and a half,
three minutes okay -
to be perfectly crisp
and slightly golden -
right and things like the asparagus
tips and the courgettes
and the chillie they're all gonna
be perfectly edible in that time.
But things like sweet potatoes
which are quite hard er -
because of the three minutes -
you've gotta cut it to a thickness
which is gonna be you know nice
and edible in three minutes you know -
so something like that -
sort of like thick kind of crisp.
So these are ready -
so just shake off the excess oil and
then lay it out on the paper - wicked.
I'm really pleased with these so basically
what I'm gonna do now is put
a little bit of salt on them -
cos I thing that makes lovely
jubbly and just test one.
Mmm - hot and crispy - Mmm - perfect.
Right I'm gonna get on now
and cook these in batches
and I wanna keep feeding the old troops
cos they're ravenous now
so I'm gonna crack on.