Naked's what I call my way of cooking.
What I cook in the restaurant isn't
what I cook at home.
Cooking's gotta be a laugh.
It's gotta be simple
- it's gotta be tasty
- it's gotta be fun.
I suppose you could say it's stripping
down the recipe to its bare essentials.
No way it's not me it's the food.
Must be a special occasion Jamie
if you're having your hair cut?
It's my birthday.
I'm having a party -
have a load of mates round
so I thought I'd have my mop chopped -
make a bit of an effort you know.
So you cooking for everyone?
Yeah yeah - I've got 'em all coming round
about 30 or 40 or them so...
I wanna keep it simple -
I've got big loin of pork -
slice it up - big salad, salsas -
shoved in a pitta bread -
posh kebabs mate - it'll be pucker.
Look at this -
now the butcher's done
all the hard work for me.
All I did was walk in the shop
say can I have a loin of pork -
can I have it scored -
can I have it off the bone -
and can you chop the bones up for me?
It's all done - no mess.
So all I want to do is do
some really simple things
to make it really taste superb -
I mean I'm just gonna roast it as normal.
So first thing I'm gonna
get some fennel seeds -
just about a couple of tablespoons
and just smash these up...
Pork's really good value and
this is a nice free range bit of pork
and it's you know - it didn't -
didn't really costs me
too much considering
I'm gonna feed about like
30/40 people with it -
These fennel seeds -
just sprinkle it onto the flesh
on the bottom yeah -
it's quite a nice fresh flavour - er -
and you know I think it complements
pork quite well - so pat that in.
If you didn't want to use this much...
could you use a smaller joint or?
Yeah yeah -
I mean I've got a big joint of pork
cos I've got loads of people coming round,
but do a half loin - do a quarter loin -
even if it's for two or three people -
do a quarter of a loin of pork
and then when it's cooled down
put it in the fridge -
it'll last for about 2/3 days -
really nice in sandwiches -
the kind of the more of
the point of roasting you lose -
you know what I mean -
you might as well just fry it
or grill it then.
So these garlic cloves -
I've just broken up the whole bulb
and I'm just gonna kind of
smash it a little bit -
just to kind of squash it really -
not smash it into a paste.
Then just scoop it out
and rub it onto this meat
and it doesn't look it's gonna do a lot
but it will infuse
an immediate bit of flavour.
So - so we've done that -
then just turn it round -
and I'm gonna get some rosemary into these
lovely cracks do you know what I mean?
So as opposed to just having
lovely crackling salt -
I'm gonna get rosemary in these
little gaps and then just -
ah it's just gonna be so tasty.
So that's the pork crackling
there on the top?
Yeah - this is the skin and I've scored -
and the butcher's scored it -
so when that cooks and
the fat gets going in between
and I've got like rosemary in there it's
gonna start sort of getting all greasy
and fatty and bubbling away and
the skin's going to souffle up
and all that rosemary flavour's
gonna go straight into it.
Pull of the nice sort of tender little
bits really and get rid of all the stalks.
All you wanna do is just
chop up the rosemary
so it's just fine enough
to get into those...
nothing exact and then kind of
sprinkle it over the skin
and the idea really is to get it
all in the gaps and not on top
because even though it doesn't matter
if it's on top it'll burn
and you won't sort of benefit
any flavour out there.
So just kind of rub it in.
Are you gonna serve this hot or cold?
Well I'm gonna serve it hot but you
know it doesn't matter if it's cold.
I think pork's wicked
hot or cold you know.
Right - what we gotta do now is do
a kind of little marinade - er - and...
we've got a nice big tray.
In that tray I'm gonna put
all the left over bits of flavour
that haven't quite gone into the pork -
all the rosemary - all the garlic -
little bits of fennel seed
and quite simply put er -
a good lug of balsamic vinegar -
just enough to sort of thinly
cover the bottom of the er - tray.
There you go - and some olive oil.
Right so I'm gonna get some bay leaf -
and these are really nice flavour
so I just pick some of these off -
so just kind of rip them up
into the bottom of the tray -
and then what I'm gonna do
is just put this lion - flesh side down -
not skin side down cos anything
that gets on the skin will burn
and we want to have
lovely golden crackling.
But the flesh side we wanna suck up
all those lovely flavours,
and just leave it for about half an hour.
Right so this pork's had
about half an hour now -
doesn't really look much different
on top cos it hasn't touched it -
but on the bottom it looks a bit different
and it'll definitely
taste a lot different.
So what I'm gonna do is
just push it to one side er -
get a nice big pinch of salt...
on top and that'll make it crackle
and go really nice.
And then a bit underneath
to season the meat as well.
And these bones that I've got chopped up -
I just put in a line -
and then just move the pork onto that
and it'll lift the meat off -
off the marinade cos you don't want it
to boil do you know what I mean -
you want it to roast...
So the meat juices then fall through...?
Yeah cos basically what's gonna happen now
is the juices will cook out the pork -
go into all that lovely marinade
which has got olive oil in it
and it's gonna be like
a kind of really sticky,
tasty kind of dressing type thing -
which will be really nice
to dribble over sliced meat later.
I can't imagine how that's
gonna look like a kebab?
No but the thing is when it's cooked
I'm gonna slice it nice and thinly -
put it on a plate - little bit of salad -
little bit of salsa, pitta bread -
It seems such an extraordinary thing
to be cooking at home?
Kebabs?
Oh mate - I know that a lot of chefs
are a bit kind of proud
but I'm not too proud -
I like a bit of tacky
every now and again -
so no - I love kebabs -
it's gonna be perfect for tonight.
Yeah - so basically
I've got my oven on full whack -
I'm gonna put it in for an hour -
after the first 20 minutes
I'm gonna turn it down to 220
so it kind of cooks nice and sort of fast
but slightly more gentle and
it'll be really nice and crispy
and golden on top and
the meat will just be perfect.
Okay to go with my posh pork kebabs - er
I'm gonna make like a funky little salsa
which I suppose is replacement
for the old chilli sauce -
so I'm gonna plonk in the old peppers -
er - right on the gas -
gas hob and that's gonna
kind of sear the skin -
and I just find it quicker
to do it like this on the gas
as opposed to in the grill
or you know to roast it.
To those two peppers I need
about half a medium sized red onion -
cos they're quite nice and sweet anyway.
And I'm just gonna finely chop it.
That's that done -
and then I've got three large chilies -
so I'm just gonna cut them in half,
and kind of poke out the er -
the seeds and then finely chop them.
Let's turn one of these.
Look at that so you wanna get them nice
and black like that.
You should only have to turn it
three times really
cos peppers normally have bout
three or four sides...
And what are you gonna
give people to drink?
Oh God! - Well we're gonna have
the normal beer and wine but er -
I've got my mate Damian coming round -
he's a really good barman and er -
he's quite good at cocktails.
In actual fact he's very good at cocktails
and he's gotta couple of little
surprises up his sleeve for me.
I don't know anything about cocktails - er
I know - he's gonna come round in a van
and we're gonna pick up
our shipment of booze.
That looks like an awful lot of chilli?
Yeah but these big ones
aren't very strong you know.
You adding them to taste really -
the idea is that's it's quite crunchy
and quite twangy and quite hot
and loads of flavour.
One garlic clove just finely chop it -
...really fine.
Lovely - let's get all that in there.
Let's have a look at these - brilliant.
Er - Yeah we're done.
So - some people put the old er -
peppers once they're really blackened -
some people put 'em in plastic bags or -
er - sandwich bags -
but I just chuck 'em in a bowl - and er
- cover them in cling film and
they'll start to steam you can see it
and then when I come back to it
in sort of five minutes time -
the inside will be lovely and sweet -
soft and the outside the skin
will just pull away really easy.
Right I'm gonna put some fresh parsley
and some basil in here.
I'm not gonna be fussy with it I'm just
gonna take the worst of the stalk off -
and then kind of roll it up -
so it's all kind of compacted
and then I'm gonna finely chop it.
Here we go.
I know it's your birthday Jamie but does -
does your party have a particular theme?
No there's no theme -
I just wanna get all my old mates
together really - have a good laugh.
I don't - I'm not really all that
keen on theme parties because -
well I had a terrible experience once -
I - it was my mate's 20th birthday
and it was cross dressing party.
Don't ask me why -
it wasn't my idea - and er -
all the girls came as blokes -
I went as a woman and I made such
an ugly woman you wouldn't believe
and I was in a luminous -
luminous green skirt and
skirt and shirt number -
and er - I decided to walk home
at the end of the night
and I had to keep diving
in the ditches cos -
cos cars kept coming along and
I didn't want them to see me.
And I didn't tell anyone that I'd left -
and they just found my handbag and
the inside of my bra next to the pond
and everyone thought I'd drowned and they
were digging around trying to find me.
So I won't ever be doing that again.
Right - so just add about sort of five
or six tablespoons of olive oil -
just enough to sort of loosen it up
and make it lovely and shiny.
And then these peppers
should be ready so basically
we just wanna kind of pull away the skin
and that's really easy now
we've kind of steamed them a little bit.
You sometimes you see people
wash them under the tap cos it's -
they think it's easier and
it's just damn lazy really
and you wash all the lovely
sweetness away - so don't do that.
Anyway - a little - little bit of
black skin left of them is quite nice
cos it tastes quite chary and -
barbecuey - which is pretty funky.
What we have to do now is cut it in half -
and you should be able
to pull out the once.
Ah they're hot!
Yeah it's an idea to let them get...
- ah - it's an idea
to let them get a bit cooler.
Ah - get rid of all the pips.
And then just chop it along
- right nearly there.
And that looks yum yum.
So right so scrape it all in. In we go.
That looks superb and all we have
to do now is kind of correct it all -
so good pinch of salt and
a really generous twisting of pepper.
Lovely! -
and actually I tell you
what the other trick is -
nice little lug of red wine vinegar
because it's got
a really nice twang and er -
kind of gives it that kick -
that little kick that we like with
the chilli and all that funky stuff.
Right so - mmm -
I'm really pleased with that.
Tastes really good now -
but if you come back
to it in about an hour
when it's all had time
to kind of amalgamate
and mix up and all the flavours are
kind of getting right in there - er -
give it another bit of salt and pepper
and er - that'll be really good.
Hello mate.
Where do you get the van?
Ah borrowed it off my mum.
What is she a builder or something?
I'm in a party mood mate -
how you feeling?
Wicked.
Promise me you're gonna
give me a hand with these punches
cos I'm useless I don't know
what I'm doing.
Definitely.
Right I've got to shoot off - get changed
but can you make that sugar syrup -
Yeah yeah yeah - orange isn't it?
Yeah orange and a bit of mint...
Thank for that - see you soon.
This mozzarella and chilli salad
is absolutely superb -
it's definitely one of my favourites.
Get it really good -
what I have to do is
just blacken the chillies -
exactly the same as I did the peppers
and I just have to prick the skin first
cos I had a bit of dodgy experience once
when I was at work
and I was grilling
about 30 chillies and er -
all of a sudden they started exploding -
I mean like really like hot hot exploding
all over my face and
it really really burnt.
So got to prick 'em first
and then they won't do it.
But they smell wicked.
I love chillies anyway -
but like when you've got that
milkiness of the cold sort of mozzarella
and the kind of sweet hot chillies - like
- to me it's just like - I just love it.
I love it to bits.
Also I've got quite a few veggies -
well quite a few -
I've got a couple of veggies
coming tonight so -
I want them to able to put
something in their pitta bread -
you know have something
substantial to eat.
These are basically ready now -
we just wanna make them sweet
and make the skin come off quick.
So I just pop in the pot and er -
cling film it.
And leave that for about five minutes.
Er - and what I'm gonna do now -
is I've got some nice mozzarella -
but I reckon the key
to make this a really good salad -
I mean it sounds a bit funny
is to have a nice big plate yeah -
and then er - instead of cutting
the mozzarella up which looks -
I think a bit plasticy -
just rip it up - and old fashion really -
I mean into quarters
is kind of a good idea.
Just so it looks a bit more
natural and a bit kind of more -
I don't know rustic I suppose.
I just think it looks funky.
Right there you go -
now these chillies you can see 'em -
they've been steaming a little bit and
there's loads of condensation inside.
I just test one and see
if the skin wants to come off.
Yeah lovely.
Right - er - they're really easy to peel.
You just push away the skin -
comes off really easy.
So what we wanna do now is get -
just take the ends off the chilli -
cut them in half -
they smell absolutely fantastic
and I just scrap all the seeds out -
right which is obviously
the really harsh hot bit -
So what you're left with
is fairly mild then is it?
Yeah reasonably mild -
I'll try one in a minute
and if I'm wrong -
I mean all chillies are different -
from different parts of the world - er -
and I've been eating chillies raw
one minute sort of really easily
and then the next week
we get a similar looking batch in
and they're from
a different part of the country
and you nosh into one and it's like ah! -
And it's just like awful but -
no I think these will be alright -
and I jut basically slice them lengthways.
So if you make a really
really hot chilli - like that -
what if that was really hot
what do you do?
It's quite hot but it's nice as well.
Oh - yeah it's quite hot -
but the thing is even though
it's quite hot - it's mild hot -
when that's with all that
really milky mozzarella,
olive oil and stuff it's gonna be superb.
What else would you use these for?
These chillies?
God - you can do 'em so much - er -
you can do 'em with like boiled rice - er
in with noodles - and I like
'em especially in like spaghetti
or pastas and stuff like that -
over grilled vegetables - in salads -
loads of stuff and just a couple
you know don't put loads in -
just a couple to sort
of liven it up a bit.
Right - so what we do now is just really
roughly sprinkle it over the mozzarella -
don't be fussy - don't do anything
sort of restauranty with it -
sprinkle it all over and that's beautiful.
So then what we've gotta do
is get some herbs -
and we've got some nice herbs.
I've got some purple basil and some green
basil and I'm just gonna rip it up -
really kind of roughly -just over it -
Purple basil is rather unusual isn't it?
I suppose it is unusual - but -
you can get it in all the supermarkets now
and you know looks great
and it tastes really good.
Does it taste different from green basil?
Slightly different yeah -
slightly fresher -
slightly more kind of aniseedy I think.
The thing I like about is even
an idiot like me can do it -
you just chuck it -
you know all this
no positioning or anything -
just chuck it all over the place.
Black pepper very important.
Just do it from a height
so it kind of scatters -
some nice sea salt from a height again.
And er - I've got some nice -
nice olive oil.
You can be nice and generous -
again just scatter it.
Would you say that's a chef's tip then?
Well no - no -
I'm not doing it to be ponsy -
I'm just doing it because
if you do from a height then -
you're not gonna get a whole load
of pepper of a whole load of salt
or whole load of oil in one place
so it looks a bit kind of you know -
...no just do it.
And lemon juice I think -
you could go for balsamic vinegar
which would look quite pretty
but I think that - I don't wanna hide -
balsamic vinegar's quite sweet
and I don't wanna hide up
the sweetness of the chillies.
Yeah - lovely -
that's gonna be really nice
and that looks fantastic.
This was a bit of a fluke really
how this salad came about really
cos I was just walking down the er -
supermarket -
getting my fruit and veg as per norm
and I was tucking into the -
the peas and er - they were so fresh
and sweet and it was lovely -
and I thought -
oh why can't raw peas work in a salad?
So all I do is just get the old peas out
and if you're lucky they'll all be small.
You do get the odd fat ball like a bullet
and you don't want that at all -
so you can either cook them
the next day in a different way -
or you could blanche them
and put 'em in the salad,
but I personally think you know
you loose the whole idea about it.
So - I've got some washed baby spinach.
All I'm gonna do is chop
the old spinach in a bowl -
chuck the little peas in as well -
I'm gonna really simple dress it.
I need some olive oil -
a good kind of four, five second lug -
you know about 4/5 tablespoons -
just enough to coat your spinach really
and then you wanna about
the same again in lemon juice
and the lemon is quite
important do you know
what I mean cos it's quite a summery
thing and lovely fresh crunch peas
and the lemon kind of pulls it
all together so it's quite important.
Just do it to taste really.
And then I wanna good pinch of salt
and a little bit of pepper
and just sort of give it a dress.
Do you always do that with your hands?
Well you can use tongs
if you like but it just -
I like to get stuck in
you know what I mean?
Makes it more fun.
So let's taste one.
Mmmm - yeah that's fine.
So once you've done that -
just chuck the old spinach on -
on the plate -
and you'll always get left with a really
lovely pile of like peas at the bottom
so once the spinach is all there -
just kind of sprinkle all the peas around.
I love all that - it just -
just reminds me of summertime so much.
And then - got some feta cheese.
You can buy - I bought this
in a block over the counter -
you can buy in a pack or
you know whatever you can get hold of.
You know funky little block like that -
and I just love it to bits.
And just crumble it any old how.
Would you use any other sort of cheese?
No to be honest with you in this salad
it's so simple and it works so well -
feta cheese is the only one
for the job because it's kind of -
it's kind of creamy -
it's nice and salty -
and it's kind of a bit tangy
as well you know
and I just think I can't think of
a cheese that would do it to be honest.
Er - and the coulour's just look great
and just sort of maybe bob it
about a bit so it gets in there.
And that's just about it.
The easiest salad in the world.
And it tastes pucker.
Lovely - I like that.
I got that sugar syrup done mate.
Excellent.
What's that Damian?
This is - this is just a sugar -
sugar syrup with a -
with a bit of orange and mint.
How much sugar and water did you put in?
Well I did a quarter of a pound
of sugar and a pint of water
and I just reduced it to a third.
That's the base of er ...?
That's what the basic is -
it gives a really fresh sort of taste.
Cos we don't need all these peels
and mint and there.
What is this cocktail thing -
what's it called?
This cocktail's called Jungle Boogie -
I made it for Jamie -
I really appreciate that.
So what you have to do bro
is chop the pineapple and er
orange and mango into hunks.
Into hunks?
Into hunks.
Hunks and chunks.
We use a white and dark rum...
the dark colour's a bit sweeter than er -
than the white one.
And it sort of balances each other out.
So I'm gonna add that to the syrup -
smelling pretty intense.
I forgot the umbrellas.
Oh no.
I wanted to have a true
Del Boy style cocktail.
Now we have to do is er - add the juices -
we've got some orange juice -
we've got some pineapple juice
and we've got some mango juice.
So have you know Damian a long time Jamie.
Well yeah - I work with Damian
and he's a choice barman - and er -
we kind of work together really -
or we did work together for three years.
Just - shall I put this straight in there?
Yeah just chuck it in.
Mate I'm sorry cos I'm getting
a bit nervous now - I've got butterflies.
How many people coming over?
About 40 but if it goes pear shaped
it's just me and you mate
and that big bottle of rum.
So we're gonna put a little bit
of lime juice in there -
gives it a bit more flavour.
Liven it up a bit.
The last finishing touch for it is to put
a bit of grated fresh nutmeg on it.
How much do you have to put in?
You just - you just grate to taste.
Bit like salt and pepper.
Yeah exactly try it Jamie.
I'm looking forward to this.
What do you think?
Yeah! - That's gonna do the trick.
You look sharp - I look a tramp -
so I'm gonna get dressed and
you look after yourself for 10 minutes.
Sure.