Naked's what I call my way of cooking
what I cook in the restaurant
isn't what I cook at home.
Cooking's gotta be a laugh.
It's gotta be simple.
It's gotta be tasty. It's gotta be fun.
I suppose you could say it's striping down
the recipe to its bare essentials.
No way it's me - it's the food.
My mate Tim's coming over from Germany
we worked in an Italian
restaurant together
and I'm just checking his flights
he's coming from Hamburg and he's
going to London Stanstead airport
and it's all on time.
Have you got anything special planned
for Tim's visit?
Not really - he kind of shook ma
little bit because I just
well you know typical me...
oh yeah we'll do this
and I said oh we should get a reunion
sorted and then he like
e-mailed me back about 4 days ago
and said I'm coming
I've booked the flight
so it was like oh oh
gotta get a party together quick.
So I'm basically just get all
of the people from work,
that we used to work with.
Do an Italian meal.
So I've gotta do a fair bit of shopping
not much it's pretty simple cooking actually.
And then I've gotta go and pick him up a bit later
I'm gonna do him a big sign
don't know what I'm gonna write on it yet
but I've always wanted a welcome
like that at the old airport.
And I've never had one.
Ah bonjourno... (speaks Italian)
Belissimo...
Can I have 10 slices of your best
pachuta my friend? Graci
You taste it?
Yeah lovely... graci
fantastic
Belissimo - can I have the mozzarella...
Graci that's beautiful...
< MOzzARELLA, PEACH
AND PARMA HAM SALAD >
Right my darling
I'm gonna make a fantastic salad
it's all around like mixed leaves
you can have what you like to be honest
but - er - let me get a plate or two.
Big plates - honestly
they'll do you a favour
buy a couple of plates and it makes
life so much easier
chuck it in the middle of the table
none of this plated up business.
which you can get in the supermarket
which it's just peppery and a little
bit more interesting really.
All you have to do is like scatter
the old salad all round the plate
really really casually
sort of one layer really
Do you always use a salad spinner?
Actually I used to slag 'em off like
you wouldn't believe.
I tell you what I've found lately instead
I mean it's dead - it's dead tempting to
buy those bags of salad isn't it?
I mean I've done it
you open them and they just go
horrible really quick
and sometimes they're bruised
or haven't been spun properly
and a bit too wet
so I just - and it's much cheaper
to go and buy your own ones
but you know it doesn't
take any more time.
Give them a little wash
spin 'em in the old salad spinner
and then if you put 'em in the
fridge with the old lid on
I think maybe because it's
protected by that
the fridge doesn't sort of ruin it
and make it sort of wilt quick
so you know it's dead good.
And then let's - I've got these fantastic
pucker peaches, pucker peaches mate.
Fruit in salads - very, very under rated
not done that much really.
You could peel the skins but I actually
like the skin personally but
just give 'em a wash.
So all I do is you just cut it like an
avocado in the middle - right - twist it
that comes out and if don't come out
it ain't ripe so you shouldn't be
using it in the first place.
Try that my old darling.
Have a nosh on that. Mmm- lovely.
And then you just rip it like that and
a ripped peach looks so much better
than a cut one. Because it just doesn't
look commercial and horrible
so I just do that to all of them.
Peaches are there.
I've got some - got some nice Mozzarella
yeah and er - got this from the deli
and it's Buffalo Mozzarella
sounds bit weird
but Buffalo Mozzarella is much
nicer in salads
it's really soft and milky as
opposed to the sort of
the cheaper stuff which
is better for pizzas.
So give it a try - you can get it
in the supermarket actually
so just open the bag up and again just rip
it into nice little mouth sized pieces
and just kind of put it
around the plate in
and around the peaches and
the leaves and stuff.
Is it called Buffalo because
it's so big?
No - it's Buffalo because
it's Buffalo milk.
But they're also very big so yeah.
But er - you're so sweet darling.
There you go.
And I think that looks amazing already,
so what have I forgotten
oh yeah - Parma ham - get this in the
supermarket get 'em to slice it for you.
Ask them if you can taste it first the
Parma ham right and if you just notice
if it's too thick, sometimes they do it
too thick and it drives me up the wall.
It's like eating a bit of old shoe...
so say can I have it a bit thinner please?
Just get a nice strip like that
and just tear it up
and just kind of almost sort of
drape it in and around the cheese
and the peaches and the leaves.
I can't really stress how fantastic
this salad is
because if you imagine like
the peppery leaves
like a bit of oil and lemon over it
fantastic yeah
salty like Parma ham right
and the milky Mozzarella and the juicy,
juicy peach.
Fantastic
Just a little bit of salad over the top
just a little
and got some lovely mint here
just kind of pick it - rip it -just a
little bit on the top's quite fresh
and I think brings the flavour of the
peaches out quite nice
and once we get a nice bit of oil and
lemon juice on there be lovely.
But I won't do that now because
I'll have to do it later
otherwise it'll kill all the salad leaves.
So you can sort of do it
this far in advance?
I can do - well - I should do it there and
then but I can do it this far in advance
and get away with it
so all I have to do now is take it
out the fridge a little bit
before I need it so it just gets
to room temperature'ish
squeeze a couple of lemons,
double the amount of olive oil
bit of salt and pepper - all over it.
Beautiful mate.
And a bit of bread with it or something?
Yeah
< TWO NUT CHOCOLATE
TORTE CHEESECAKE >
Two nuts chocolate torte cheesecake mould
but you can pretty much use
anything you like really.
I just find it easy cos
you can click it out.
Butter - 250 grams of butter.
What do I need? Oh - grease proof paper
- right -just rip off a bit
little square that you know
is gonna cover it yeah?
And what I do - bit like making
a paper airplane
actually it's nothing like making
you fold the paper in the middle
and then you turn it around
fold it into the middle.
Then you basically you just keep
folding into the middle - like that
I do one more - so you guess
or much that is into the middle
put your finger where it is
and just rip it up.
Ohh - lovely! - So that's gonna
line the bottom yeah.
We just need to get a bit of butter on it
and that'll stop anything from sticking.
So just very thinly line the bottom
and the sides
and just put a bit of butter on this.
Yeah - lovely - and then stick that
on the bottom - nice and snug.
Right - so there's nothing gonna stick.
Right - forget that now.
So - I need 300 grams of nuts
it's called 2 nuts Taut
because it's got two nuts
in it basically
we've got walnuts and almonds
and I need 150 grams of each yeah
which is pretty simple to remember.
And these are 100 gram packets so
there's 100 grams of almonds
and I'm not gonna get the scales
out or nothing like that.
Just pour out the nuts and divide
it into two - same with walnuts
I think where at all possible not
use the scales okay.
So just divide the old nuts into half again.
What I'm gonna do - got the old Magimix
chuck the nuts in there - okay.
And we're gonna whizz it up until it's
a powder - 30 seconds, 40 seconds.
Lovely - so look what we got yeah
it's fantastic
that's what it should be
it's like powder.
Right chocolate - it is a chocolate Taut
we need 300 grams of chocolate.
One we're gonna put here - two
I'm gonna crumble up 200 grams of this
and chuck it in with the nuts and er
we're gonna whizz that up as well.
Makes a bit of a noise but you just wanna
break it up into pieces. - Alright?
Better than watching telly.
Anyway we'll lose this into a bowl
now we're gonna put the butter in here
just plonk the whole lot in there
rip it into two or three.
We need 100 grams of sugar
lovely. And pour that in.
And that's just for a little
bit of extra sweetness.
And we wanna whizz this up for about
whip - I wanna whiz
whizz this up - so it gets nice
and shiny and creamy.
So I need 6 eggs yeah - cor
organic of course.
I'm gonna crack my eggs in
here very carefully.
And then what I do - I pinch the
yolk and plop 'em in one by one
and that's gonna really enrich and that.
And make it nice and silky and beautiful.
Lovely - all you have to do now
is get it all together
so just mix these up until
it's nicely mixed.
Right - now the best bit
egg whites.
Flavour -lift - we have to
get 'em together,
but I wanna get these really stiff
so at the last minute
add a good pinch of salt and that
kind of helps it to be stiff
and whip it up my old darling.
I've got a bit of a mad day because
I've got - got to go and pick ...
has given me some mushrooms for
the main course and
and now I've gotta go and pick up
Tim from the airport
so I can't be late otherwise
the poor old boy
he thinks he's going into London
cos it's Stanstead airport
but it's not as central
it's out in the wilderness where I come
from so he'll be getting... London
Jamie where are you?
Done. Right so - er
add a little bit first
fold it in just to loosen it.
Now as it's air that we've
got in the egg whites
what we need to do is get it in
there into the mix
without sort of knocking all the air out
of it - otherwise it won't rise.
So what we do is we call it like
a folding action
do sort of movements like that that kind
of fold in from the outside to the middle
and maybe change and go from
the middle to the outside.
It's good for a couple of days
I mean when it's got a bit
stale just crumble it up
and add some ice cream over it.
Mmm- baby - so here we go.
Shake it so it's flat.
And you can cook it straight away
but the reason I held this other
100 grams of chocolate back
if you get the chocolate and
just push it in with your finger
and just sort of put it here
there and everywhere.
Cos when they cook - when you cut into it
you have that lovely like sea of chocolate
that lovely taut and then there's just
a little bit with like running chocolate
that comes out - it's fantastic
and I love that.
Beautiful - in the oven
about 190 for about an hour
just test it with a little knife
if it comes out clean - we're off mate.
Cool. Let's go
How are you?
I'm alright mate
Alright
Have you got those mushrooms?
Yes I've got them
Good man
I spent all day yesterday to
collect those mushrooms
And they're beautifully honestly
they're nice...
Show me show me show me...
Okay hold on a minute... I'm too old.
You're not too old mate. - Look at those
yeah... fantastic...
oh thanks mate - that's brilliant.
Listen... cos I'm going on
the train to pick up Tim
I've bought my own box cos
it fits in my bag
can you just put
I only need half of that lot...
...this is too small...
No no - it's only for 7 people
just half of those...
Half of these
...I collected these mushroom
you just wanna bloody half of these
mushroom... hold on a minute...
Hello Jamie Baby... hi how are you?
How are you?
Great not bad at all.
Right you ready for tonight?
Yeah that's great - so what's on the menu?
Secret mate - I'm not telling
I'm not telling you anything...
Cheers...
So I'll see you a bit later...
I'm all day in side
See you Tonight
See you later
Bye
< SEA BREAM WITH
MASHROOMS & POTATOES >
So are you happy to see Tim?
Yeah it's fantastic seeing the old boy
still on good form - he's just having a little sho
Getting cleaned up cos I said he's
I said he smelt.
So what we got is thinly sliced potatoes
in the tray - the oven's on full whack.
A really nice seasoning
potatoes and salt and pepper
you can't really go wrong
roasted, fried, whatever.
Add a little bit of olive oil.
Just enough olive oil to coat them really.
And just sort of with your hands
just - you wanna make sure every bit
every slice gets a bit.
Just lay 'em out nice and flat
so it's like one layer
whack 'em in the oven
for about 15 minutes.
Give 'em a nice good roasting yeah.
So while that's cooking got some nice
mushrooms from Ginaro - right.
And I'm a very big mushroom fan.
I've got Chantarelle here
got Girolle here - the classic...
old oysters - trumpette d'amour
and pierre de mouton.
Right - they're not cheap.
But I think wild mushrooms have character.
They have a certain flavour, certain
texture - they cook in a certain way.
It's turned something very - quite normal
into something that looks exciting
and that's what it's all about.
If you haven't got much money get
don't use button mushrooms
forget them forever - get your Chitakes
or your field or Portobello mushrooms
slice 'em up - cook 'em well with
a little bit of this
and maybe a little bit of dried mushroom
porchini - morrell
they're quite expensive but
you need the smallest amount
and it will liven 'em up and
make 'em taste fantastic.
Most supermarkets stock little
punnet of like...
Do you wash them?
No - well Girano very kind of him
has clean them up for me
but with wild mushrooms if you wash them
they'll soak up all the water
and they'll cook and taste of nothing
you're diluting the flavour.
What you do is you brush them with a brush
and you get like maybe trim them up with
a knife and I'm gonna fry these off
so first of all - I'm gonna just chop
up a little bit of garlic
just about two cloves really
just for flavour.
Olive oil right - hot pan - and I'm just
gonna put the mushrooms in.
And then the garlic - when the mushrooms
cook the water will cook out of the yeah?
And normally that's when people think
oh they're cooked.
What I will say is let the water come out
carry on cooking it
cook the water away and then there's
so much flavour in that water anyway
cos it's from inside the mushroom
let it cook back into it again
and then you get that nice
fried thing happening.
The other trick is
get a good bit of salt and pepper in it
now cos like mushrooms are like
they're like sponges really and when
they cook... sucking it all in
and if it's just a little bit
of oil and garlic
well then yeah you know it's not
the end of the world,
but if you've got salt and pepper
then it's like yeah
it's tasting good you know. So - next
bit is the old fish and herbs so...
I would like to serve this with Sea
Bass but it's not always available
and it's quite expensive,
so I've got Sea Bream
and I think they call it Royal Bream
cos they've got a little crest on its head
which is supposed to be a crown.
So what I'm gonna do is I haven't
got a plastic board so
so I'm just gonna put a bit of cling
film on the board
cos I don't like fish
fish on wooden boards.
Why's that?
Well just you know you get
fish juice on the old board
and then you go and make a cheese sarnie
the next day and it tastes of fish.
Not very nice. So anyway.
Put your old fish on here -these herbs
I've got some flat leaf parsley
and I've got some purple basil
but you can use any fragrant delicate herb
I would
I wouldn't use tarragon but you know
things like green basil, dill, fennel tops
so right. With the fillet - lovely fillets
I pinch it at the breast - breast
it's not a chicken!
Right pinch it at the fillet yeah
so it kind of puckers it up yeah?
And then you just at an angle slice
like that -just a little bit
with all of them. You can do one,
two, three, four slashes
we'll just go listen can you hear
starting to fry.
So it's starting to you know it's gone
shiny now and the moisture's gone
and they look fantastic
I'm turning it off.
And what I'm gonna do now is just er
with my hand just kind of
open up that slash yeah
little touch of salt to get
it in the cracks.
Pinch some herbs and just sort
of push 'em in there to the gap
just you know gives it the flavour
a little tickle.
Just finish these old fish.
Right - so the fish looks pucker.
Potatoes - yeah - yeah - they're soft
well they're cooked,
they're soft and they're slightly
golden which is just what I want
just gonna let 'em cool down a little bit
cos if we start wanting to move 'em
about they'll just break
because they're hot.
Nice knob of butter into the old mushrooms
at this point when the heat's off
and that'll melt and we'll squeeze in some
lemon - probably only need one.
Yeah lovely! - Nice chunk of parsley
right - potatoes
get like a palette knife or one of these
and just sort of - where's my old cloth?
Here
Right - basically just scrap
up the potatoes
very carefully because you don't
want to break 'em
so they'll be a little bit stuck
but they'll be nice and golden.
Whether you do this for two people or ten
just simple - simple, simple simple.
Put all these lovely mushrooms and all
the juice - don't leave anything
all the herbs - get it onto the old potatoes
you can mix it up anyway you like really
make sure that mushroom juice and butter
and flavour goes on to the potatoes.
And just shake it - so it's flat right
and it just looks so damned good now.
The fish is going on top yeah
skin side up.
Right - and it's going in the top of the
oven so the fish skin will become crispy
but because this is already cooked
at the bottom right
you're gonna heat and cook it a touch more
won't get that much heat.
But it will steam and all those lovely
mushroom flavours will cook into the
into the fish and then in return the
fish is gonna sort of like
all the juices will cook out the fish
and go into the potatoes. Lovely.
So now we just drizzle it with a bit of
olive oil - make it go crispy.
In the oven for about five, six minutes.
I'm gonna make a sauce to go with the fish
It's called Salsa Verdi and it's an
Italian word for - green sauce
which doesn't sound quite as impressive
does it - so we use the Italian.
But basically... sounds like Tim's
got the old basket ball...
and we need to finely chop it.
Oh Timmy come and give us a hand Tiger!
Coming
Alright handsome - eh
looking very swish mate.
Mmm- you smell good too...
So what you like me to do then?
I've got some herbs in the old
in the old frigo
you can have the big board because
you're a tiger.
I'll get you a big chopper
there you go mate - big enough?
Thank you - that will do
So what sort of herbs have you got there?
Tim chops up herbs?
Basically we've got parsley,
mint and basil
and classically it should just be
parsley but I like the basil and mint
cos it lightens it up a bit and
it's going with fish so
kind of makes sense to me.
I finely chop my garlic
I need some gherkins - gherkins, mustard,
capers and anchovies - there you go.
So we use about 7 anchovy fillets
Very strong flavours?
Yeah
Smells nice -just chop 'em up.
It's a bit of chopping
I mean to be honest you can do
this in the Magimix
it's just that I think that when you
do it by hand it looks a bit more rustic...
I have a connection with Germany before
before I met Tim
was my first girlfriend
her name was Helgar Buge right?
She was German and I was about 12 and she
was about that much taller than me.
And I went out with her for 2 weeks
snogged her mate
...China in your arms,
giving it some of that...
smooching, dancing, and I really like her
and then she chucked me.
She chucked me and I cried and - but then
when I went to youth club the next week
everyone was laughing at me cos she told
'em that I kissed like a cartwheel...
but it wasn't me - it was her fault anyway
cos she was so tall
I was like... like a goldfish
I suppose but...
I've learnt since and I've improved.
I love gherkins and I think it really
really gives
you have these in Germany?
Yeah they come from Germany
Is that where they come from?
What they called?
Well in Essex we call 'em wallies...
Anyway - capers right -just a nice
handful of capers. Drain the old water.
And you know what we're looking
for here by this stage
when we've chopped a bit is - same
parts - equal parts of capers,
gherkins and anchovies right.
As much garlic as you want to taste
yeah and then when you look
at that whole pile
that should make up like one part to sort
of four parts of the chopped herbs.
And if you do a bit more or a bit less
it's not the end of the world,
but what you're doing is varying the
flavours and the tanginess.
And you can vary it if you're serving it
with meat - or boiled roasted meats, fish
even sort of like grilled vegetables and
stuff like that are fantastic so...
that looks beautiful mate.
Just whack it in that glass bowl
there's some half decent
olive oil over there.
I add it to loosen really...
so quite a bit... little bit more
yeah that's lovely. Two big teaspoons of
that French mustard my old darling.
And that looks good mate.
So I'm gonna add all of this to here
and we just stir it all in
it's nice and loose with the olive oil
and that's what you want
so it's kind of you know it'll
just fall off the spoon.
But if you taste it now - it'll be
it'll be kind of bland yeah
so you need to liven it up a little bit.
You need something acid like vinegar
or lemon juice and
personally I prefer vinegar so start off
with about two tablespoons.
And when it's all mixed up
give it a little taste.
Little bit more. Can you put a bit
of salt in there my sweet?
Just do it to taste - but
talking about taste my old darling
show Pat your - your tongue ring...
Can you imagine having that
done to yourself
I mean I couldn't do that as a chef
because you'd lose all your
taste buds wouldn't you?
You don't at all - you don't taste
in the middle of the tongue
you just taste on the edges... like you
know - you don't taste in the middle.
It just seems a bit scary to have a
blooming great rod of metal
put through my tongue. Cool - taste...
Fine
Pucker - that'll be nice - that'll be
even better in about half an hour.