Naked's what I call my way of cooking
what I cook in the restaurant
isn't what I cook at home.
Cooking's gotta be a laugh.
It's gotta be simple. It's gotta be
tasty. It's gotta be fun.
I suppose you could say it's striping down
the recipe to its bare essentials.
No way it's me - it's the food.
You do not believe how happy I am to see
not that I'm not happy
to see you all the time
but I've just been shopping
with George for an hour
and I think that's enough
punishment for any man.
The worst scenario is - is when they pick
up two things that they like
one that they really wanna buy
and one that they don't.
And it's kind of like er-er-right
er - well darling they're both very nice
and there's kind of like the
sweat starts dripping
and it's which one does she like and
I pick the wrong one - no I got it wrong.
She's meeting up with like six
really good friends today
and they're all gonna go clubbing
and she's allowed me to tag along
thanks very much.
So we're gonna you know have a good night out
and then they're gonna come back
to the flat and kip over.
I've gotta provide munchies and service
Jools says my payment is to hang
around with me and my mates,
so I'll just have to ham
it up to the boys.
What did you do last night?
Spent it with six lovely ladies.
Thank you.
I am gonna make the most fantastic
breakfast in the world
and it's called Pukkola
because it's pucker and my
name's Jamie Oliver.
And I've been searching for years
for like the perfect breakfast
yeah like a muesli type thing
let me show you how you do it.
Right - so I've basically got about
8 scoops of organic Scottish porridge oats
yeah - so that's the base really
that's the main thing.
And then I want about two handfuls of bran
and then I've got some dried fruits
right which are quite nice cos they're
yeah - I love dried apricots because
to me they're like wine gums.
If I ever had a kid right who just wanted
to keep eating wine gums all the time
and had a problem with rotting teeth
sounds nice doesn't it?
I'd just give him these cos
I think they're fantastic.
The second one I've got is dates
and these are dried
and they're sweet and they're chewy
and they're caramely
you know I hate anchovies, I hate dates.
But you won't be able to
taste it as a date
it'll just be like a
like a flavour really.
So have you been practicing your dancing?
Yeah! No I'll let you into a secret yeah
I am probably the world's worst dancer
I don't think I'm going to be impressing
the girls tonight too much
do I try and be cool and
get it completely wrong
or do I just walk in there
as my normal self
and just you know have all the
girls walking home saying
he's nice that Jamie but
he's a terrible dancer.
Oh yeah - anyway look you can
see it's all chopped up now
it's actually quite sticky - quite most
- so - put that in there...
So that sweetens the - the mixture?
Yeah we're talking about
natural sweetness here,
so the next thing we do
are nuts my old mate.
And I've got three nuts and
a handful of each yeah.
I've got my almonds which are great,
I've got the old Brazil nuts
now almonds and Brazil nuts are great
cos they're a white nut
and when you smash 'em up they go
almost really creamy
and sort of powdery which is lovely.
And then I've got the er
the walnuts which are quite
you know quite a robust sort
of nut flavour.
And then just - you can do it
in a Magimix if you like
but I just like to fold 'em up
like this and...
Just bash it with one of these...
It's good to get all your
aggression out as well.
I haven't had a drum for a while so...
or you can use the Magimix.
No I like it
I tell you what's good about this
and you won't get this from the Mag
is that you end up with lovely like
you get lovely kind of
almost bruised flour
and then you get lovely chunks as well,
and I think you know it adds to the
flavour and the er - the look really.
So all I do is mix it up now.
And turn it over.
Now there's no way that
I'm gonna eat all this
so what I can do is just whack it
in an old air tight container
and I have this every
morning for breakfast
and you know quite frankly
just gets your brain working.
Gets everything working actually.
This is like the Viagra of meuslis mate
Anyway what's different about this
because by all means like you know
just serve it in a bowl and
have it for breakfast as we all do,
but what I'm saying is just, about an inch
over the cereal just cover it with milk
so there's quite a lot of milk
in there - lovely!
And that'll suck it all up and go lovely
and then I need like apples
so I've got about enough for sort of four,
five people in there.
So I usually do a round sort of
half an apple per person.
You do nice long grates and you can see
you get all the lovely green skin
they're real crunchy boys as well
just don't buy the soft ones
get the real crunchy boys that are quite
almost a little bit tart as well you know
But also if you think about it
like if you look when I'm grating
there's quite a lot of juice so you've
got that whole sort of apple
apple skin, apple juice thing
and it just makes it taste so good.
I tell you what else I've done
with the dried stuff yeah
I've made - well I was cooking flap
jacks for my cousins the other day
and I just carried on like normal flap
jacks but put the dried stuff in
and I used that - and it was actually
better than normal.
It was really, really fantastic.
Lovely! - So we're done mate.
So basically that's it - it's quite sloppy
but the thing is as I said you
can eat this like that now,
but if you leave this is the
fridge for like 8 hours
the whole thing just changes
do you know what I mean.
You maybe want to add a little bit
of milk when you serve it
but basically it goes sticky and Moorish
and scrumptious and like all the flavour.
The thing is all the - all the goodness
comes out of all the dried fruit
and the nuts and into the milk and then
into the - you know - it's fantastic.
I cling film it yeah
cos well not that I've got anything
that smells in the fridge,
but if you've got say like some
strong cheese or some onions
or anything like that the milk
and the porridge oats will take
that flavour on and you don't want that.
So - you're gonna love it
I'll let you have a bit later.
< SWEET PEA
& PRAWN RISOTTO >
I'm gonna make a bit of lunch
are you up for that?
Lovely. Got some frozen stock and I just
put a bit of hot water over it.
I'm gonna make risotto - I'm gonna make
like a sweet pea and prawn risotto
it's fantastic.
Did you make that yourself that stock?
Yeah - does that impress you?
Lovely - do you hear that
...er - yeah it's nice - you can use
cos you can use like the old
stock cubes for risotto
but they just taste so much
better you know
you can't really go wrong if
you start with a good stock.
So a good stock - good start already.
Second thing we need is onion,
garlic, a little bit of celery.
Thing about risotto - people are scared
of them - are you scared of them?
A bit
Do you have dreams about them darling?
Bit of a dodgy nightmare.
Listen - all this is chopped up yeah
put a bit of olive oil in there
just a little bit. And -er-right-so
basically you can hear it frying now yeah,
so what I'm gonna do is just
give it a little shake,
put a lid on top and because
you've put the lid on top
all the moisture that comes
out will go back down
and it'll kind of almost like simmer
and steam a little bit so that's good.
Just cook that for a couple of minutes
to get it nice and soft.
Get all the flavours happening
you know what I mean
that oil and the root veg - this should
be getting nice and soft now.
Let's have a little feel - yeah.
And it's just kind of a good
start flavour wise
so the next thing is the old risotto
rice and risotto rice is like
it's quite a short plump rice with
loads and loads of starch.
So 50 grams per person - in my case
half a handful cos I've got big hands
in your case a big handful.
And then just stir it around really.
Now I tell you what I would do now is er
put a little pinch of salt in
yeah because you want the seasoning to
get inside of that rice as well.
It's only a little details,
but it does count.
The first thing the rice is getting is
just sucking up all that flavoured oil,
all the lovely vegetables and stuff.
And when it's - it stops you know
almost like a simmering steaming sound
you can almost - when it starts
to sound like it's frying
I wanna put a little bit of
white wine in there.
About a glass - and you look in there now
all of a sudden there's this creamy stuff
has come out the rice you know
you wanna kind of encourage that out.
So by moving it you can see it like
just becoming sticky and lovely.
So you wanna cook this for about one
or two minutes and just smell it
and when you can't smell that kind of
that harsh kind of alcohol thing you know
you know what I mean by that, when you put
the old brandy on the Christmas pudding
when it - it stops smelling like
alcoholic, which is now basically.
You can start adding the stock
and you'll just be left with
all that lovely fragrance
so just tip a bit of that in there.
So you want -for the perfect risotto you
add a little bit of stock at a time.
And never anymore than that really.
And then as it cooks - it'll cook into
it and you know it's kind of
by stirring it - all the kind of risotto
rice is kind of moving about
and hitting each other. And...
And is the heat quite high
when you're doing that
It's kind of - the heat's medium high
if you have it too high
the outside will be cooked and
the middle will be like raw.
If it's too low it'll just go
like pulp so you wanna
medium kind heat you know
so it's constant.
Think risottos are fantastic
they take 20 minutes to make right
yeah you've gotta put a bit of love
and affection in there
you've gotta stir it a little bit
but big deal you know.
And once you've learnt this like say
you just make a couple of risottos
over a couple of weeks and you've cracked
it yeah - you've cracked the risotto
the basic risotto - next time you go
shopping and you're a bit stuck
well I can cook risotto so what's good
having a little walk around
spinach - baby spinach - fantastic
throw that in at the end with
a little bit of lemon juice
beautiful - nice Parmesan over the top.
Asparagus - you know you can
put any sea food
open up like clams or you can just
put 'em straight in.
How brilliant is that.
I tell you what I'm so hot
I've got this dripping sheep on top of me.
Oh dear oh dear - so let's have a little
taste of this now cos it's looking lovely.
How can you tell when it's nearly ready?
Well I just got a rice grain
and you eat it.!
And basically you want it to be soft and
a pleasure to eat and if it's not
if it's chalky or - or you feel
like you need a glass of water
after you've eaten it then no
you cook it for longer.
So it needs about 2 more minutes cooking
which is perfect cos I've got
well I'm cheating but...
- who's gonna tell me off - I am at home.
Got some lovely - right they're defrosted.
Got some lovely frozen prawns which are
really actually juicy and nice
and tender yeah and they look lovely
beautiful colour and they're
already cooked anyway
so they only just need to be like just
cooked with the rest of the rice
for two minutes and then
I've got this petite pois
and don't tell me who hasn't got
these in their freezer
cos just about everyone has
unless they're food snobs in my eyes
because frozen peas have got
to be the most
well they're the best frozen thing
in the world aren't they.
And I guess you could use
fresh prawns and...
Yeah yeah fresh prawns of course
and I like I feel like I'm compromising
but at the end of the day
I'm only feeding me and you
and it's you know it's not as if
I've got the Michelin star guide
coming round to give me a telling off.
So no - it's you know
it's what's in my freezer and it's real.
I'm gonna add a little bit more stock
and I think we're practically there
and now I'm gonna turn the heat off.
This is the most important thing
that I found in risotto yeah
so we turned the gas off right
no more heat.
And I wanna nice knob of butter, yeah
so let's get that in there.
And that's just gonna kind of
bring it all together
and be absolutely tasty as put
a knob of butter in there
and just kind of knock it up a bit
and just stir it in.
And we put a lid on and just leave it
forget it for 2 minutes.
If you just serve it now the rice will
go on the plate and the stock will go
and you'll have a plate of...
and then you'll have a pile of rice.
But what you want is a nice ouzy
so it's nice to eat.
What I want yeah just as a last thing
I love all that - it's so fresh.
I've got mint from the garden yeah
and mint's great - you just plant it
it grows like the clappers.
You just cut the old boys right down
and they grow back up again.
They've got no feelings at all
they just keep growing. But
If you look at this now it is just so
creamy and lovely, it's just ouzy you know
it's not gonna - it's gonna be nice
and juicy - let's have a look.
Mmm -just a touch of salt and pepper
right - we do want it to be perfect.
No point in going to all this trouble
and then you know it's a bit bland so...
I tell you what's amazing
the amount of sweetness
that comes out of those peas and prawns
it's lovely.
So put that in the middle of the plate
I've done a bit too much as always
and then get your mint and from a height
just kind of sprinkle it
and it's lovely to get - almost like
you've got the lovely flavour there,
but you have a bit of freshness on top.
And now just squeeze
this over the top yeah.
So there we go
right what else do we need?
Here - I've got some
a really good peppery olive oil yeah
just a little drizzle
and that's just you know
it's almost like a bit of pepper on top.
Taste that oh gorgeous one
go on - do you like?
It's delicious
I'm gonna make er - a chocolate desert
like we call it a chocolate pot yeah
it's probably about the most simple
chocolate thing in the world.
But the good thing about it right
is cos the girls want chocolate
and I'm not arguing with them
at this time of night.
I've got half a pint of
single cream yeah
that I just pour in the old
in the old pan.
I don't wanna bring it to the boil but
I wanna bring it to a little simmer,
so I'm gonna whack the old gas up
and get it heating.
And most importantly - got chocolate
70% cocoa mass for cooking.
But if I put a whole chunk of chocolate in
it's take half an hour to melt so by...
by smashing it up does a good job so
there we go right I need some eggs.
I've got some lovely free range organic
eggs -just stand them up for a laugh.
Basically what I wanna do is er
just crack the eggs so I've got
the egg yolks yeah
I'm not using the egg whites
so I'm gonna chuck those away,
but basically the egg yolks I'll put in
this dish - it just makes it really,
really rich and like intensifies
the chocolate flavour.
So this cream has been on the heat for
about a minute - a minute and a half
so it's dead quick really and that's the
only bit of cooking that we've got to do.
So it's not boiling but
it's pretty much like a
well it's kind of like a simmer really.
So pop your old chocolate in
right - let's get a spatula right
and just stir this in and I love this bit
because you see cream turn into
like this pretty unbelievable thing.
The liquid's hot enough to
melt the chocolate?
Yeah just hot enough to melt the chocolate
and also these egg yolks
I'm gonna put in now as well and obviously
eggs hardly need any cooking really,
but you've gotta stir it while
you're doing it
cos you don't want scrambled eggs
in your old chocolate.
The nice thing is that you can see it
becoming like really, really smooth.
So now we've done that what do we need?
- A bit of brandy mate.
Don't tell them about it cos...
I think they've had their fair share
for this much I put about a tablespoon
a tablespoon and a half yeah
but the trick is
cos all brandy's are different
and I wouldn't use a cheap old horrible
brandy, do something half decent.
But have a little - stir it in and have
a little taste yeah because like brandy
and chocolate is quite a nice combination.
But if you have loads of booze
and you swallow
and it's like oh... horrible so.
So the brandy really is just for flavour?
Mmm- yeah - little bit more. The other
thing you can is like grate like orange in
a little bit of orange zest so it's like
the chocolate orange effect mate. Yeah
Nothing better than the old chocolate
orange. Right the last thing I need
I'm gonna put a little bit of butter yeah
and sort of you know it's about 20 grams of butter
but in layman's terms
about a small knob of butter really.
It's purely there to sort of enrichen it
and make it lovely and smooth
and just kind of...
Is it salted or unsalted?
That is actually slightly salted
funnily enough chocolate can always do
with a little little pinch of salt
cos it actually benefits from being
seasoned a little bit
Do you really not mind coming home in
the middle of the night and then cooking
I can't think of anything I'd like less
No, mate I've done worse - every time I go
round someone's house for a dinner party
I end up cooking even if I'm not cooking so
it makes no odds to me mate.
Listen that's gone all nice and smooth now
I like to put it in little expresso cups
and fill 'em up with chocolate
pour it in carefully - I'm sure
I'm gonna get chocolate everywhere.
It sets really smooth and
like just like the perfect thing
ah no I spilt a bit...
you know it's not hard and horrible
it's kind of very smooth and lovely.
Darling - we're starving...
I'm nearly done now but I've got to
put 'em in the fridge.
Did you have a nice evening Jools?
Yeah it was brilliant, we had a
right laugh, really good
I'm afraid we're really starving
no pressure
Oh that's alright
But can we have that now?
No no no - cos I've gotta put them in the
fridge but you can have that
Excellent - don't be long.
Easily pleased
Look what I've got...
You could serve them very happily as
they are, but I tell you what I do
I do like a little
little like lemon and palenter cookies
but any like little crunchy kind
of biscuits fantastic
cos then you put 'em on the
side of the old dish
so you have three biscuits a bit of this
teaspoon and it's nice cos you can
kind of use the biscuit
to sort of spoon it all up.
So there you go - about half an hour,
forty minutes - so...
< MIDNIGHT PAN
COOKED BREAKFAST >
This is like probably the most unchefy
thing I've ever done in my life right
basically I invented this when
I was about 16 years old yeah
and what is was we used to go
we got... and we used to go down to the
pubs and to have a drink right?
And we weren't horrible little reckless
little kids but we did you know
take part in a bit of underage drinking
and I had two very close friends that
used to live quite nearby and they always
used to come back for a bit of tucker.
So I developed this thing which I call now
midnight pan at breakfast
because you make it at midnight
and it's cooked in a pan
and it's breakfast kind of
I've got a really nice non stick pan
and that's quite important for
this recipe I think.
And I'm gonna put the sausages in there.
Is it very hot?
It's like a medium high heat - if it's too
hot everything gets kind of coloured
and cooked far too quick and
it's raw in the middle
well like I hate eggs when they're cooked
and they've got a black kind of
that horrible teary film on the bottom
and big bubbles you know
a medium sort of high constant heat's good.
Well I'm starting off with the sausages
cos they need more cooking yeah
so the second thing we need is er
yeah mushrooms.
So I've got some mushrooms
and tomatoes here yeah
so got these lovely like field
mushrooms which are fantastic
just turn it up a little bit.
Just - you can see - the sausages
are getting nice and brown
and I slice the mushrooms quite thick
about a centimetre thick yeah
sort of like that. And actually if
you cook field mushrooms well
and you don't put too many in a pan right
they taste so fantastic.
You can use any mushrooms you like
just don't use button mushrooms
which I think are like the worst
mushroom in the world
so as soon as you put 'em in
cos they're a little bit like sponges
toss 'em over and they get all that
they get all that lovely juice as
well and kind of make one layer.
What we doing next? I'm gonna cut
these tomatoes in half yeah
and I'm just gonna like put them
cut side down in the pan
and like all this is cooking at the same time.
Like this is the easiest fry up
cos you can see it all happening
and like as long as you get
your orders right
you know your sausages
cos they take longer
then your mushroom, then your tomato
then get your bacon in
and as long as you get that right it's
it's just easy peasy.
So I've got some nice bacon here
and this is dry cured bacon
pretty normal bacon from the supermarket
and you can feel it's dry
cos it's not got all the horrible water in
it doesn't shrink so much you know.
So like people do cook things
really badly and I've
honestly I've been to some of the poshest
hotels and had the most expensive
and the worst fry ups of my whole live.
You know - how at 28 quid for
a fry up and it's like...
You know I'd much rather go down
the greasy spoon
and get an alright one for 2 quid you now.
We want the bacon to be nice and
crispy so while that's happening
I've got the grill on and
I'm gonna do some nice thick chunky bread.
I like thick - you know thick toast
oh... it's beautiful. Here what you up to?
Just getting some orange for the girls.
How's it going?
Lovely! - Right so I'm gonna whack
the old toast in now
Babe can you get us some butter out of
the fridge and butter some toast for me?
I can get it out the fridge but I'm not
buttering it - I've got guests.
Do you hear that? - Did you hear that?
See this is what I'm in my house for...
What did she say?
No to be honest I'm looking after
the guests. Dear oh dear.
Look at the old tomatoes now - they've
gone nice and brown
yeah look at that.
Now this is the trick right
It's alright - it's me. Things like pine
nuts and toast I always forget.
And I burn... Right... get the toast in
So basically this is the clever bit now
what we have to do is jingle
and jungle everything up so every
little area side to side
middle to middle - everything's gotta a
bit of everything do you know what I mean.
What we're gonna do - we're gonna crack
the eggs in and just kind of angle it
so the whites kind of go
a little bit everywhere
and what we do is we do it
sort of from side to side and
what happens is it kind of sticks
everything together which sounds repulsive
but believe you me at 12 o'clock at
night it sounds beautiful.
And means that you can like cook it and
then put it on to a big plate and it holds
it's like a big frisbie mate.
It's like obviously very classy
and then you put a little bit
of pepper over the edge
yeah I'm really pleased with that
and then... oh Gawd...
Alright - right so toast nearly
burnt but it's blooming good
perfect cooking for me.
Right so - what happens now is now...
now the bottom's had a you know
it's perfect cooking - I'm just gonna
pop it under the grill for
literally 30 seconds just so the top
of the eggs get nice and coloured
so we're done - let's get...
Let's put the thing on there, lovely...
I keep the eggs nice and soft, and there
we go, that is the world's best fry up.
Don't tell me if I serve
that to the Queen right
I tell you what she will be chuffed me
old mate. Right girls come on...